Good evening everyone. Uh I'll now call
to order uh this April 1st, 2025
meetings of committee of council. Uh Mr.
Harris, can we please begin with a roll
call of members? Yes, Madam
President. Mr. Mr. Med here, Mr. Royo
here, Mr. Cle here, Miss Craig, Miss
Diaz here, Mr. Hirs here, and President
Baker here. I expect Councelor Craig
presently, but she is excused at this
time. Um, a few reminders for everyone
at the top of the meeting. Good evening.
I ask that you please silence your
phones and devices if you haven't done
so already. And a reminder that this
meeting and its participants are being
recorded. Tonight, we have meetings of
committees of council. There are no
general public comment periods during
this meeting. However, committee chairs
will call for comments from the public
for legislative items, which means bills
and resolutions that appear on the
agenda. Comments and those times are
limited to three minutes per speaker and
must begin with your name and block of
residence for our meeting record. I
understand that there may be many of you
in the room uh this evening to hear the
report uh of to council during our
public safety committee meeting. I want
to thank you all for being here and I
also want to be clear that this report
requested by council isformational and
not legislative as I mentioned before
and therefore there will not be public
comment during uh excuse me taken after
that report. Uh before we begin
committee uh meetings we have the first
item on our agenda is the approval of
the March 3rd 2025 committee meeting
minutes.
Motion to approve. Second. We have a
motion and a second on the minutes. Are
there any council comments on the
minutes
hearing? None. Mr. Harris. Mr. Man. I.
Mr. Royer. I. Mr. Gleas. I. Miss Diaz.
I. Mr. Hush. Hi. President Baker.
I. All right. Our first committee
meeting this evening is finance. Council
Royo. Thank you, Council President. Uh,
we have three items on the agenda for
this evening's committee meeting. Uh the
first is the budget update for the year
end of 2024 and the first quarter of
2025. I'd like to invite Director
Campbell uh to come up for the uh budget
update.
Good evening. Good evening.
Um, so you have received a summary and a
detailed budget report for both the year
end of 2024 as well as the first two
months of 2025, not quite the quarter.
Um, because today is the first day of
April, March books are not yet closed.
Um, so the latest month we have to
report on is February. Um, we're going
to review both of these reports this
evening, though my main focus is going
to be on the 2024 year end report.
Um, just as a little reminder, uh, per
the home roll charter, we're we will now
start to provide you with monthly
reports. Um, both the summary and the
detailed written reports that you
receive this week. Uh, because we need
time to close the month, uh, we
anticipate that you'll receive those
reports from the previous month by the
20th of the following month. So, you
would receive the March reports um by
April 20th. And in addition, we plan to
present a budget update report such as
this um at a council committee meeting
once per quarter. Um because this
process is new and really just
beginning, I welcome any feedback for
what you would like to see in these
reports in the future and how to make
the process better. We'll continue to
refine it as we
go. Uh so to the reports tonight, um I'd
like to start with the 2024 reports. As
I said, I'll I'll mainly be be focused
on those this evening. I'm going to
speak from the summary reports that you
received, but I'm happy to answer
questions or or to uh take questions
about the detailed reports as
well. Uh I want to begin by saying that
these are unodudited reports. Um if
you're familiar with audits, you know
that during audits, there are journal
entries needed or other adjustments that
may result in different numbers included
in the final details of the budget. uh
but those are details and the numbers
that you see this evening will remain
approximately the same. So overall we
ended the year very well. Uh most of the
departments and the enterprise funds
ended the year better than budgeted. Um
in the general fund that's the first
page of the summary report that you
received. Uh you can see that our budget
was approximately 73.4 million for the
year. This is for the general fund not
for the enterprise funds.
On the top of that page, you'll see the
revenue. Actual revenue is showing at
about 71.3 million or approximately 2.1
million less than we budgeted. However,
uh this number is a little bit
deceiving. Um as you're aware, we must
have a balanced budget in the general
fund each year. This is a this is a
requirement. Um and in order to do this
sometimes we use cash reserves uh either
as uh to show to show a revenue meaning
that we're using a some cash reserves to
cover expenses or it shows on the
expense side meaning that we're showing
a a surplus so we're putting money back
into the cash reserves. Cash reserves
are really the opposite of other lines.
So you want to see an expense um and you
don't want to see the revenue coming in.
um get to my notes here. So um the
original budget as I said of 73.4
million included a transfer from cash
reserves of approximately 2.3 million.
That was to cover expenses and our
expenses from the general fund were
approximately 2.2 million less than
budgeted and some of our revenue in some
of the other lines meaning in our mainly
in our community planning areas exceeded
budget. So we did not need the cash
reserves and ended the year with
approximately 1.2 million in surplus um
that will go towards increasing our cash
reserves. Um most of the bureaus in the
general fund came in under budget and
this was due to variety of reasons but
mainly um savings from some staff staff
vacancies that we had. All of the
departments worked very hard to cut
expenses beyond those vacancies,
including using technology to figure out
how to be more efficient. Um, which
helped to adjust um some some staffing
levels as
well. Um, in the enterprise funds, three
of the funds, water, storm water, and
trash were budgeted to end the year in
2024 actually in a deficit. And unlike
the general funds, this is allowable
because these are enterprise or um
function as business funds.
The storm water fund uh did end the year
with a deficit, but the deficit was
approximately $400,000 less than
budgeted. Um so it came in better better
than budgeted. The trash fund also ended
with a deficit of approximately 70,000
more than budgeted. However, we have not
yet received one grant which is the act
101 recycling grant. Um once that is
received, this deficit will be less, but
we don't know what that ending amount
is. So we didn't add that into this um
to this budget.
The water fund was budgeted to end with
a deficit of approximately
860,000. The team again worked hard to
reduce this over the year and they
actually ended with a slight surplus of
700,000. And the sewer fund was budgeted
to end uh with the surplus of
approximately 1.1 million. Um that was
the the one of the four enterprise funds
that was um showing a surplus. Um mainly
meant to build build the cash reserve
there. and we ended the year with a with
a larger surplus of about 3.9 million.
Um this really helps to establish an
emergency fund in sewer um which we we
haven't
had. I'll talk very briefly about the
February 2025 reports before I stop for
questions. Um it is really too early in
the year to say much of substance about
these reports. There aren't any notable
items that are standouts at this time.
um as there hasn't really been enough
time in the year to um to see those
trends for for spending. However, I will
note that some of the line items, if
you're looking at the detailed lines,
will look like they are already all
spent. Um this is mainly due to
incumbrances, which is really a hold
that is put on funds for purchases that
we know will happen at some point in the
year, but it hasn't happened yet. So,
we've included these holds in the
expense line because they will happen.
Um, but the cash might not have gone out
of our accounts yet. And as we move
through the year, these funds will be
spent. So, we're simply showing that
spending from the
beginning. All right, I'll stop there
and and ask for questions. Thank you,
Director Campbell. I'll open it up for
any questions from the committee,
if I may. Councelor Diaz, I have just
one question. There was a I believe $10
million grants for cities that may want
if they're struggling in some area and
that was by Governor um Shapiro. Are you
aware of that? Are you looking into that
grant at all?
Yeah, I'm not sure which grant that that
is. You said it was for 10 million. I
think it was for 10 million. It could be
for more. I just kind of took a quick
glance of the the fact that it did came
out. I could also forward it to you.
Yeah, that that would be great to see
that. Thank you. That's all I had.
Any questions from full counsel?
Councelor Med. Thank you, uh, Council.
Thank you, Director Campbell. Um, my
question is, are we um do we do we uh
project that the revenues and taxes will
meet the budget for Q1? I know it's
still a little bit too early to say, but
are we all paid from a revenue side? We
are. So, again, it's it is a little bit
too early in the year to talk about, but
um one of the things that happens is um
real estate taxes are are collected at
the beginning of the year. So, those are
those are coming in um now. We'll see
those it it you know increase especially
through June here. Um so, yeah, at this
point everything's coming in as we have
planned. In fact, some of the revenue
again in the community planning lines is
coming in a bit higher than we had we
had projected.
Thank you. And
um it's good to see that you know some
of the losses we projected were not as
heavy and we were able to mitigate some
of those expenses. Um do we project that
those expenses will we'll continue to
see that trend in 2025 as the year goes
on? Will we be able to continue to
mitigate some of these expenses? That's
our goal. Um
um yeah, I mean we never quite know how
the year is going to going to turn out,
but we're always looking to decrease
expenses if we can. So yeah. Uh thank
you. My final question is how much was
returned to the general to the reserves
uh last year and where are the reserves
currently at for 2025?
Um so when you say last year, you mean
2024? Yes. Okay. Um so it's about 1.2 2
million um that'll be returned to the or
that that that's a surplus to go into
the um cash reserves. Um we're
anticipating um it about uh well over 2
million this year because of the earned
income tax increase. Um and a lot of
that as we talked about in the budget
process is really to try to increase um
the cash reserves because we feel like
they haven't been at a good level um for
for emergencies that might come up.
Thank you. And that concludes my
question and thank you for the report. I
think this is helpful to have this on a
monthly and quarterly basis.
Director Campbell, just to piggy back
off of that, um what's the recommended
percentage for our reserve fund? Um so
it varies based on municipality. Um we
are trying to get between 15 and 20%.
And that's up the budget of of the
operating annual operating budget. Yeah.
Thank you. Yeah. Any other questions or
comments from
council? Right.
Thank you for the
uh thank you for the uh budget update.
Um we'll move on to the uh second item
on the agenda which is administration
resolution number
252025 amending the capital improvement
plan funded by 2018 loans. Sorry.
Yeah. Just stay here for this one. Um so
um the other director Campbell is
handing out um some updated uh project
details for this. So you would have
received this list already in the um in
the committee packet. Uh but this gives
a few um updates to the project status
which is the last column um in those
wanted to to give you some of that so
that you can see which projects have
been completed and and how that um has
been adjusted.
So, um, these I'm going to talk about
these.
Both of them. Yes, please. Thank you.
Um, I'm going to talk about both of
these together. That's what I was
actually just getting ready to say. Um,
it's two different resolutions. Uh, one
for the 2018 bonds. Um, and those the
2018 bonds is the the sewer fund. Um,
and then one for the 22 bonds. Uh, those
are the water funds.
Um
so yeah, as capital projects um are
completed or or need adjustments um once
the actual work on the project begins,
we need to make shifts um within line
item allocations and each bond fund to
accommodate these adjustments. Um and
most of these adjustments require
approval um of the amendment from
council and that's what we're bringing
to you this evening. This is a a
regularly occurring process. Um so
you've reach re received these changes
in years past. We we did another one of
these in March 2024 at the finance
committee meeting. It's not allocating
any more money. Um but rather it's a
request to move money between the
already approved projects. It's very
hard to estimate exact costs for
projects and bonds as many of the
projects take you know many years to
complete. So, this allows us to close
out projects that may have come in under
budget um and move move funding to other
projects that were already approved um
that may need more funding. So, again,
two different uh plans that require
adjustments and therefore or two
different bonds that require adjustments
and therefore two different resolutions.
So for the 2025 bond or 2018 bond funds
which is 20 resolution 25 2025
um we have a number of of shifts that
are that are occurring in the the line
items there. Um the shifts total about
2.3 million. Um you see all of the
details in the
2018 go or general obligation bond
exhibit A and those are all projects as
I mentioned connected to the sewer
funds.
um these there's no new projects
proposed in this 2018 bond fun
financing. So all of these projects have
already been approved um in in previous
uh council meetings for the 2022 bond
funds which is resolution 26 2025. Uh we
also have a number of shifts that are
needed between the projects as some are
completed and others need additional
financing. Um those shifts total about
5.3 million and those details again are
all included in the 2022 GO bond exhibit
A that you received. Um and those
projects again are all connected to the
water fund. When the 2022 bond funds
were approved by council, they approval
was for um there was approval for
administration to transfer funds within
certain categories. Um so the transfers
that you see in this exhibit this
resolution 26205 are from one c one of
those categories to another. Um so the
two categories in the water fund um are
from the transmission and distribution
and work at the two plants the Konosoga
and Sesuana plants. And in addition to
these transfers we're actually
requesting two new projects to be added
for the Knosoga plant. Both of those are
related to membranes at the Konosoga
which are the treatment technology
there and I think I will stop
there. I'll open it up for questions
from the committee
from councelor. Thank you. Thank you,
director Campbell, for the presentation.
And are there any projects being delayed
or cancelled or reduced uh as the result
of this amendment?
No, they're not being delayed. Um I am
not aware of any being reduced. Um
Director Campbell's shaking his head.
No. So, no, I don't think any of them
are being reduced either. Thank you.
Any additional questions or comments
from council?
I'll just um mention one thing if I may
councelor Royo is that when you look at
the phase three large um TND Sesuana
River to water treatment plant um that
is the design phase that's been
completed. Um we're now in phase three
and that's where the Penvest uh
financing that we were talking about
related to this most recent bond. Um
that's the project that some of these
bond funds are going to go to. So, and
we need additional to complete that. And
I'll also just say that um you know the
expense of um buying steel pipe uh is
changing and that may impact um how much
uh replacement we're going to be able to
do, but that 42-in main replacement is
significant and a major focus um for for
this year. And we'll be talking a bit
more about it in the public works
committee as well. Yeah.
Great. Thank you, Mayor Sachi. Um, any
questions from the
public? This would be in regards to
either uh resolution 25 or
26. Darling Bird and Street. Once again,
I'm going to ask council
um why they do not put this information
up on the screen that you're showing. We
spend a lot of money updating city this
city council chambers with
technology and yet you're talking about
things that we're not able to see. It's
not available on the website at this
time and it needs to be put out to the
public. One of the reasons when I was on
the home row and suggested even about
the reports was that so the public would
have more information not just the
council members. So again I'm asking
council hoping to get an answer why this
is not presented to the public so we can
see what she's referring to or what
anyone's referring to when they're
presenting something. Thank you.
[Music]
Tony Dastra, 700 block New Holland
Avenue. I want to echo what Darlene's
saying. Um, you know, municipal
government is where we as the people are
supposed to understand how government
functions on all levels. This is the
smallest level. So, this is the school.
And years ago, I was encouraged that,
you know, if I want to see the work
actually get done, I need to go to the
committee meetings. And that's why I
started live broadcasting the committee
meetings as well as city council. So, I
do feel that Darlene's right on the
money. Like, these these materials
should be prepped and prepared and
presented on the screen cuz even when
you're viewing from home, which I've
done recently a few times, all you see
is the agenda. It's not really an
educational experience for the
residents. It's just noise on a screen.
So it it really is imperative to the
public that these get prepared and
presented. Thank you.
Just for clarification, these uh and I
agree, I think we could present these as
well. I think uh these are presented on
the website prior to council meetings
and prepared for public availability.
Hi, um Brian Nelson, um Columbia Avenue.
I just had one question. You mentioned
the vacancies um that you were using to
like we're saving money off of the
vacancies. Are there any plans to fill
those vacancies or you just going to
leave like not hire for these positions?
What's the plan going forward with the
vacancies that you guys mentioned? Is
this in regards to the budget update? Um
oh, was that for the budget? Oh, I I
apologize. I think I mis misinterpreted
that. Um but yeah, um yeah, so I guess I
mean going forward, I guess for like you
know, we're talking about the budget and
stuff like that. Are we budgeting in for
2025 to fill these vacancies or is that
not going to be budgeted in? Yeah, happy
to let director Campbell answer that
question regarding in general personnel.
So um yeah, so many of the uh vacancies
that happened in 2024 um were included
in the budget for 2025, but many of them
weren't like full vacancies. It was uh
people that had left positions. So there
might have been a gap in uh filling that
position before another uh person came
in. Thank you, Director Campbell.
With that, I will motion I got something
to say.
Susie Gomez, 100 block of North
Reservoir Street. Um, I just wanted to
implement for the the public, not so
much for you guys.
Um, what Janet had uh mentioned, $10
million of the Josh appro fund that was
granted to municipalities should have
been used. As Tina Campbell mentioned,
she's relying on the income tax um
increase from the taxpayers that was
granted for the um home room charter. So
when you're looking at a budget, I think
that all of these factors should come
into play. Especially when you're trying
to balance a budget and you have
deficits, it's important to utilize the
grants that is given to especially
crisis areas or for municipalities that
deal with issues in the community that
the government is releasing funding for.
Who writes these grants, Tina? Why is it
not important for you to, you know, push
a little bit further into looking into
these grants? Because $10 million is a
lot of money that could have been used
for these areas. And for it to be
ignored is beyond my
understanding. Any further public
comment? All right. As it pertains to
resolution number 25, uh I will motion
to move resolution number 25 to the next
full council meeting.
Second. All those in favor?
I I'll move on to uh resolution number
26. And uh I'll motion to move
resolution number 26 to the next full
council meeting.
Second. We have a second. All those in
favor?
I moved. Council council president. That
concludes the finance committee meeting.
Thank you very much. Uh now we'll move
to our public safety committee meeting.
Council.
Um I just wanted to first inform
everyone that um just like uh President
B said, there will be no comments um
during the time that Chief Mendes is
doing his presentation.
Um there has been some drastic changes.
Um, and I picked that up when um,
councelor Roya ran the budget meeting
where there was no comments from the
public, which was very odd because for
years there was um, and at that time
they were written comments that were
submitted, although I think someone
needs to look to see why it has not been
updated. But I would like um, if Chief
Mendes could please come and speak to
the public. Um, thank you very much.
All right. Good evening everyone. Thanks
for having me.
Um, so first I'd like to start off uh
with a little bit of the training that
your police department does. Um, you
know, as I've stressed numerous times
over the years, uh, Langster City has
one of the best trained police
departments, uh, in the RA around. Um,
and we dedicate a lot of our time to
training. Uh, some of those, and I guess
you guys are getting a packet, which I'm
going to summarize off of and read as
well.
[Music]
Um, some of those, uh, trainings include
control tactics, which are defensive
tactics, uh, arrest procedures, and
subject control. Can we ask him to bring
a mic closer?
All right. Uh deescalation techniques.
Uh these are techniques resolved uh to
resolve conflicts peacefully. Uh we
train in mental health awareness uh
understanding and assisting individuals
in crisis and bias training uh
addressing implicit and explicit bias in
policing. Uh some of the specialized
training areas uh our officers uh go
through are advanced patrol officer
certifications. Uh those cover safety
priorities, decision-m and patrol
tactics. Uh we require yearly use of
force trainings. Uh these trainings
include again decision making, control
tactics, deescalation principles and
post incident
care. And one of the trainings we really
focus on is realitybased scenarios. Um
these are done to enhance decision-
making verbal skills and deescalation
techniques as
well. That's a lot of our internal
training that we go through. The bureau
also does a lot of external training
programs. Uh some of which include
crisis intervention train team
certification. Uh the art of reading
people, trauma informed training, uh
which we partnered with our social
workers on and the entire police
department went through that training.
Um and we continue to to train that as
well. Along with those trainings, uh
we're we're mandated through MOPEC,
which is the certifying police agency
for the Commonwealth. Um we do yearly
updates that are required again by
MOPEC. Uh some of those again mental
health first aid, use of force and
deescalation,
uh tactical communication, understanding
stereotypes, bias, critical
decision-making models. Um the overall
key principles are those are ethics,
values, proportionality, and the
sanctity of human life. Uh and again,
these are all mandated through the
state. Your police department has a
commitment to training. Uh we mandate 16
hours of training a year. uh that they
have to go through. Uh that's mandated.
Again, they take an additional training
as well. Uh and one thing we're really
proud of with your your officers is to
show how dedicated they are since
January of
2024. Uh they have conducted over 150
hours of training on their own time.
They come in uh they volunteer to come
in. They work with training instructors
uh before shift, middle of the day, on
weekends. uh this is uncompensated time
that they spend to make themselves
better at doing their job. And we're
really proud of that uh for the the
amount of work the officers put
in. Again, like I stated, uh we do a lot
of external trainings. Uh CIT is
probably one of the biggest ones.
Um and just be sure that your your
police department is committed to
getting better. Um, as I've said
numerous times, no one's perfect. Uh,
but I will say this. You have one of the
best police departments uh around. Um,
and and we're committed to training and
getting
better. All right. Now, I'll move on to
I think what everyone's here for, our
use of force report and reporting
procedures. Uh, the police department uh
language police officers may only use
force when it is objectively reasonable,
proportional, and necessary given the
totality of the circumstances. These
circumstances include, but are not
limited
to, force necessary to affect an arrest,
control an individual, lawfully detain a
subject, prevent escape, or to protect
themselves or
others. We have a use of force policy
that's been on our website since 2022.
Uh, I would recommend everybody read it
thoroughly. There's a lot of information
in there. Uh, there's definitions. Um
there's a lot on our website and again
it's been there since
2022. Officers will follow a use of
force continuum uh which is a guideline.
Um it it will show subjects uh
resistance as well as officers uh
reactions and what they can do to
overcome that resistance.
So, I'd like to point out that the
degree of force used depends on what the
officer perceives as reasonable and
necessary under the circumstances. Uh,
the bureau expects an officer to employ
only the force necessary to accomplish a
lawful
arrest. I wanted to break down some
levels of resistance for for everyone.
Um again as the continuum we use is like
a book. It'll have levels of resistance
and our levels that we'll use force. Um
officers can enter at any level. It it
depends on the what the uh subject is
presenting them. Um but we do like to
start and and if possible work our way
up as we go through that uh levels of
resistance um which is in our use of
force policy. But I want to touch on a
couple things. Psychological
intimidation is the first level. Uh that
can be circling an officer, surrounding
them. Uh it can be inciting a crowd to
come around them. Um it can be the
thousand yard stare where they're
staring through you. Uh we train our
officers on, you know, uh keys to to
recognize. It could be clenched fist,
body blading. Um those are all
psychological intimidation.
Uh next would
be verbal non-compliance. Uh this would
be the subject's direct refusal. Uh they
could be arguing um stalling. Uh you
know basically they're not cooperating
um
verbally. Next level would be passive
resistance. The subject is either
sitting or lying down. It can be they're
refusing to let go of something. Uh
scenario with that would be a steering
wheel in a vehicle. Sometimes uh
subjects that don't want to get arrested
will hold on to a steering wheel. So
that would be that level. Uh after that
the next would be defensive resistance.
That can include fleeing uh you know
they're fleeing the officers. It can be
pulling away uh refusing to be
handcuffed. And then next would be
active aggression. That would be
delivering strikes, you know, hitting an
officer, kicking an officer, um actively
uh assaulting an officer. And then
lastly on that would be deadly force.
That would be where the officer believes
um his or her life or the life of a a
citizen is in in jeopardy uh with the
life of them. And typically those would
be a knife, a gun. Um it can be, you
know, many things that would cause
serious bodily injury or
death. Levels of control. So again, as I
said, it it's uh we use like a book
format. So I went over that.
Um all use of force starts out with
officer presence at a scene. that's uh
considered a use of force. Uh most
times, and as we get into stats a little
bit later, the mere presence of an
officer in uniform will get the results
they want. Um and and it it's you you
don't have to go past that level. Uh the
next level an officer can use would be
uh verbal direction. Um those are
commands. You're under arrest. Don't
move. Put your hands behind your back.
Verbal commands.
Uh after that would be soft empty hand
control. Uh these are control
techniques. Um they can be joint locks.
Um you know any movement that any way
you want to control movement. Uh and we
also have OC spray uh in that level of
res uh of
control. From there it would be hard
empty hand
control. Those are strikes uh to a
person. um those uh they they're hard
empty hand control because they have a
high higher probability of injury to the
officer or the subject being
arrested. Moving on from there would be
the intermediate weapons level. Uh that
would be impact weapons. A baton uh or
taser falls under that that that uh
level of
uh of control as well.
From there, um, lastly would be deadly
force. Um, and again, that would be the
officer fears for his or her life or the
life of a community member or citizen
that they have to protect and take
immediate
action. So, I want to just, you know,
touch on, you know, everything that, you
know, is in our use of force policy and
our guidelines or guidelines under title
18, chapter 5, general principles of
justification. Um everything we do is
based on whether it's uh crimes code,
case law, um best practices in
policing. Touch a little bit on
deescalation. So when safe and feasible
to do uh and given the totality of
circumstances, officers shall attempt to
take action to to prevent or decrease
the need to use force during an
incident. Uh such techniques we use are
persuasion, advice, uh providing
warnings prior to using force. Um that
can be as simple as you're under arrest.
Um trying to talk to them uh rather than
have to use any type of force. Establish
a rapport when possible. Uh engage in
communication, evaluating whether the
you can use time, distance, or
positioning. And uh when appropriate,
request additional resources. Uh, one
key thing with deescalation is it it
requires time and distance and also not
everybody can be deescalated. There's
things that factor into whether you can
deescalate somebody or not.
Also, I'd like to point out uh we do
have a duty to intervene policy. So, if
an officer sees excessive force, uh
force that would fall outside of our
policies and procedures and standards,
uh they are required under our policy to
intervene, uh when they see that.
[Music]
Folks, we're going to let the chief
continue his report. Thank you.
All right.
All right. Next, I'd like to move into
reporting a little bit. And again, our
that policy is on our website to show
reporting requirements. Uh we have a
separate policy uh for documenting use
of force
incidents. So, officers shall complete a
police bureau use of force report prior
to the end of their shift. So if if they
meet one of these uh these marks uh we
require them to report that doc re
finish that document before their their
shift ends. So before they go home for
the evening or day they have to get that
paperwork done. Uh some of the you know
the the list we of when they would need
to do a use of force I'm going to go
through because I think it's really
important. Anytime a person has been
physically struck by an officer. Anytime
a chemical agent is used against a
person. Uh so anytime OC spray is used,
we do a use of force report. Uh anytime
a conductive electronic weapon is used,
so that would be the taser. Um if that's
used, they have to do a report. Uh any
impact weapon is used, uh if a firearm
is pointed in the direction of a person.
So when you look at some of our stats,
which we'll get into, uh the deadly
force stats, it may look like they're
higher. Uh we require anytime a a
handgun is used, if they're clearing a
building, somebody pops whatever reason
and it they it's pointed in their
direction, uh we require them to do
reporting on that as
well. Uh anytime a canine bites a
person, so if uh canine uh is engaged
with someone and bites them, we require
report uh any injuries uh that are
visible to the officer or complaint of
injuries.
uh anytime someone complains about the
force. So if it's a an arrest that you
know doesn't necessarily meet the
standard, but uh the comp somebody
complains when they're being arrested
that force was too much will require a
use of
force. If anyone requests medical
treatment for an injury they they say
happened um you know even if it appears
to be an older injury and they're saying
no, it happened now. Uh we'll require
officers do reports. Um, we have a
couple caveats in there that any
supervisor can mandate an officer do
one. So, if uh a supervisor is at a call
or or you know, for whatever reason,
they can mandate an officer does
that. And also, if an officer just feels
like they they they should do one. So,
um if they're like, well, you know, I
didn't really didn't really meet the
level of any of our standards, but I I
think I should do one, then they can do
that as well.
touch a little bit on the review
procedures for those. Um, so I know I
mentioned this before, but I'd like to
point out again that when we review use
of force reports, uh, it's a 1989 case
law. I'd really recommend if anyone's
interested in use of force and policing
that you spend some time and review the
case law of Graham v. Connor. Um, and
what came out of that case was the
objective reasonable standard. Um, and I
think the simplest way to put it is, um,
we have to view it through the lens of
the officer at that time with the same
training,
same, you know, if the same exact
location
um, what they're witnessing at that
time. We can't come back in Monday
morning quarterback and say, "Well, you
should have thought of this." Like, we
have to put ourselves in that officer's
shoes at that time. what a reasonably
trained officer would do when met with
the same
circumstances. That's the guidance of
it. And again, that's a 1989 Supreme
Court ruling that has uh withtood the
test of time since then. So, our review
procedure, uh, like I said, the officer
does it at the beginning of his shift,
his or her shift or at the end of his or
her shift. Um, it then goes to the
officer in charge. So that is typically
a lieutenant who oversees that uh
platoon of officers. Um that officer or
that lieutenant is required to read all
reports, make sure they're done
accurately, review all body camera
footage and car camera footage. Um and
then if any, you know, corrections need
made or if there's any issues, um they
can address it there. After the officer
in charge reviews it, it gets sent to
our training cadre is a group of uh
officers that are trained that do our
conduct our training and review all of
our use of force reports. There are the
officers that are certified to conduct
the training uh that we train throughout
the
year. Uh from there the training
sergeant will uh I'm sorry. From there,
the training sergeant will assign it to
a group um and a training cadre member
will review it. They will again read all
report, view all video, make sure it
falls within our training and our
policies and procedures.
Uh and again just to point out at any
level of this somebody reviewing it uh
can raise an alarm and say hey I don't
think this is right or or I think
there's an issue with the
training. After it goes through the
training training cadre it then gets
assigned to the appropriate division
captain. So typically uh you know if
it's a a use of force done by a patrol
officer the patrol captain gets that
report. Uh same if a detective uses
force, a detective uh detective captain
will get that. Uh that captain again
reviews all reports, body camera
footage, uh gets the input of the
training
cadre, whether it meets the the
standards or not, if there were any
issues, what they they were uh what the
training cadre recommends. Um and then
after the captain approves it, it gets
forward to the chief of police for
another final review. Uh again, review
all reports, all video, see if there's
any issues, look at any remarks made by
training
cadre. Um and at any point along this
process, our internal affairs can can
step in and look at it as well. Uh if
they don't, for you know, whatever
reason, uh once I'm done with it, I send
it to them for the last final review and
then enter it into our system, uh as
final. Um so that's the process for
review. Um just wanted to touch a little
bit on you know if there are issues that
come up obviously we can you know if
there if there's a issue we can we can
discipline but um some of the levels
we'll do with uh discipline would be it
could be a training issue um that we
need to retrain um we could have to do
coaching uh I think the easiest way to
describe coaching is if uh the officer's
force was correct they they had every
reason to use it but there were other
options that we would like them to look
at we can we can uh do a coaching
form. Uh internal review investigation
policies again um if there's any
violations of that uh we can move on to
disciplinary action as well. Uh annually
each supervisor shall ensure that their
personnel review applicable law and
provisions of this policy. Uh the review
shall be documented and retain retained
within the police bureau records. Um, if
you're carrying any weapon, you have to
be certified in it and trained yearly.
Uh, and we maintain those records as
well. All right. And I think if we can
move on to some stats now.
No, he didn't say a word involved with
the training.
All right. So, the first stats we have
are calls for service uh resulting in
arrest. Um, and as you can see, the
larger block, uh, the color is not the
best on this screen, uh, but the bottom
larger block is the cause for service
with no arrest. Uh, moving on from
there, it's arrest not requiring force.
Um, so you make an arrest and it doesn't
rise to a level of of, you know, um,
requiring a force, a use of force
report. Uh, and from there is the arrest
requiring force. That's the line on top
um of
those. And just I'll just do quarter
four for example.
Um out of
8,698 calls for service, 477 arrest, uh
29 of those required a use of force
report uh for one reason or another. So
those are those datas as as you can see.
Uh next is all all incidents of force.
Uh non-physical incidents of force
versus physical incidents of force. Um
again a non-physical incident of force
would be something that did not require
uh the use of force reporting.
Um you know and as we talked about in
our our use of force continuum even
officer presence is a use of force
verbal command. So if it if those would
be the arrest under that data. Um then
followed by the physical incidents uh of
force. Next
one. All right. All incidents of force
by type. Um breaks it down a little
simpler as we talked about. As you can
see, officer presence, verbal direction,
uh all the way up to deadly force. And
again, I just want to make sure
everyone's clear on the deadly force. Um
it's not that deadly force per se was
used. it's that if you know if you
pointed a gun in the direction of
somebody, we require that to be a
report. Um, so that would generate that
that number as
well. All right, moving on to some
progress from, you know, of the bureau.
Uh, again, in 2018, body cameras and
revised our use of force policy, our
social worker program has been uh a
tremendous asset for the police and the
community.
Um, as I stated in the training, all our
officers have gone through
traumainformed training. Um, you know,
our recruitment and um, our recruitment
and hiring efforts as well. And
something we're real proud of is our
plea accreditation process. Um, it's
been about two years. I think it felt
like 20 at times. Um, but again that was
going through a rigorous process, a
review of all our policies, procedures,
our how we operate our equipment. Um,
and you I think it's 139 points that we
pull proofs for. Um, and while we're
almost there, uh, April 24th, we have
our we go for the official meeting to
hopefully be an accredited agency. Uh,
it just doesn't stop at April 24th. Uh,
we're continuing to work. Um, this is a
never- ending process with accreditation
and pulling proofs. Um, changing
policies, making sure they fit the most
recent best practices uh for policies
and
standards. Uh, less than 1% of calls for
service result in use of force. Um, you
know, again, our police social worker
program has served hundreds of
residents. Uh, we're really proud of the
community engagement office with
Sergeant Todd Greger, uh, and all the
work he's done, uh, for for the
community, uh, engagement. Um, he's
really taken it to a whole other level.
We partner with Blueprints. Um, we do
ride alongs with them, uh, target, uh,
those in need, uh, for addiction
recovery.
We have a partnership with Benchmark uh
for our youth intervention
um and increased youth crime prevention
efforts through uh engagement and our
SRO's as well. Um we get a lot of
compliments on our school resource
officers and we're extremely proud of
the work they do. A lot of it goes
unnoticed. Uh you might not see it or
hear about it, but uh the relationships
they're building with uh students uh in
the school district has been uh
tremendous and and we're extremely proud
of that as well.
Okay, some youth gun seizures since
2018. As you can see, um, you know, it's
been increasingly alarming. I know we've
talked about it, uh, at least since 21
when I was patrol captain. Um, we're
seeing an increase in our youth carrying
firearms and you can see the stats
there.
Um I think uh you know what stands out a
lot is you know from 24 and younger uh
the amount of guns that that we're
seeing yeartoate youth gun seizures. Uh
as you can see um there is 17 currently
and those are the age groups for the
year so far. So we're on pace again. Um,
and it's a number that, you know, we
would like to see be zero.
Um, and lastly with the stats again,
youth gun seizures for 18 and under. Um,
you can see the age groups uh with that
as well. Um, and again, it's it's
alarming and it's something that, you
know, we we really need to fix as a
community. Um, but we need everybody to
to help with that.
Okay. And that is by year going back to
2018. My stats person just uh wanted me
to make sure
you Okay. And that's all I have. And if
you have any questions for me, I'd be
happy to try and answer them.
Chief Memphis um is allowing um one
question per city council.
Does anybody
So, does anybody have a question for
Chief Mendes?
Uh, thank you, uh, Councelor Diaz. Uh,
and I I have several questions that I'll
ask. Um um first um with the most recent
incident um that most people are here
for with the March 2nd given that this
involved minors is there a separate use
of force policy and is there a separate
reporting standards uh when it involves
minors? So our use of force policy is
the same and our reporting is the same
for uh any individual with uh as far as
our reporting for use of force. Okay.
And then when there is use of force um
and reports the findings, how do
residents currently access them and are
there ways that we can make it more
accessible for residents? So I believe
they're currently quarterly. Uh we're
putting out our stats quarterly on our
website with uh the use of force data.
So that's uh that's been on and I I
think it's uh do we go back a few years
with that one that's currently on? So
it's on our website and quarterly access
only. Well um and given that um these
are quarterly can we have request
reports quarterly to the council similar
to the finance quarterly reports uh to
kind of go over uh the use of force
within the quarter and the findings.
that be something that council could
request by report
as far as the stats or I'm not sure what
you're I'm sorry I'm having trouble
hearing you with the background what
incidents happened within this quarter
what were the findings um and just a
report to council similarly given yeah I
would see I don't see an issue with that
as why we couldn't do that yes thank my
last question is you know um given that
you You stated that the review is viewed
in the lens of an officer that is fully
trained. Is there any consideration in
if this officer had previous incidents
or his past or any of that?
So that's two different questions.
Um we view it each incident on its own
standing and merit. So that's the first
part of the the the answer I guess I
would say. Um now if an officer violates
a use of force policy or any policy for
that matter then we use other violations
to increase discipline and our
discipline is covered under the
collective bargaining agreement which
we're bound by as well. So um again each
incident we have to view for the
incident. Um, I'll also add because
that's a very good question, our our uh
the way we track our stats and the
system we use, we have early
intervention alerts. So, we set it um if
if there's the the mark is set and an
officer reaches that for numerous
different things, not just use of force.
um if they get to that level, uh all
supervisors, internal affairs get an
alert and it'll say like, you know, hey,
officer so and so had six use of force
reports in this time frame. Um it needs
a second look and then we we require
supervisors and IA to look into that um
and see if there's a pattern of of
something there. Um and it's not just
use of force, we do that for vehicle
pursuit complaints. Um there's level
there's thresholds and if they meet that
um then we review it. Um we also do
random um body cam reviews. So we have
supervisors randomly pulling up body
camera footage um to review the officers
as well. And again those are
accreditation standards that we have to
meet uh continually as well. Uh that
that concludes my question.
Is there anyone else?
Thank you, Conor Das. Thank you, Chief
Mendes for the presentation. Uh, what
immediate steps uh is the department
willing to take in order to increase
transparency and rebuild the public
trust?
What's what steps are we willing to
take? Yes. To transparency and we build
public trust.
Well, I think public trust is a two-way
street. Like, you know, we have to work
as well.
If you have to come to the table and we
have to talk. So, we for everyone in the
room tonight, we're we're going to
conduct this meeting so that we can hear
everyone. Chief And
yeah,
we will meet people where they're at. As
I said about our community engagement
office that was created in you know I
forget the year but the past few years
the work they've done has been
tremendous. The accreditation process
was an outside agency or an outside
entity reviewed from all across the
state. We don't know these people. They
come in they they they reviewed um they
looked at everything. Um our we put our
stats on online. Um, you know, we're mil
again, we're willing to do everything,
but again, you know, we we would welcome
uh people's involvement as well. We have
the uh citizen police academy we're
going to launch again. I would I would
love to see that packed. We tried to do
it last year and it it we didn't have
enough people interested. So, come to
Citizens Police Academy. We will tell
you how we do things. We will put you
through scenarios. I would open that up
to every council member as well. uh any
future city leader uh any community
member come our doors are open we will
have it um I think we're shooting for a
June time frame I hope it's so packed
that we have to run three this year or
more
uh another question are there any
limitations to create a review
board if they are what are they how they
can be addressed so there are
limitations and I believe the mayor's
going to talk about that in a report she
has
Okay. Y and how is the relationship now
between the police department and the
community?
I think it's great,
but I mean we're a city of 60,000
people. Um
I think it's it's great. Can there be
improvement? There can always be
improvement. I' I've never said the
police are perfect. We're perfect. Um,
but the strides we came um from 2018,
I'd really even say from like 2021 or
2022 to now has been tremendous.
Everybody up here should be proud of
their police department. The community
should be proud of their police
department. They work tirelessly. We're
the shortest we've ever been, but our
clearance rate on crimes is amazing. the
engagement from our community engagement
office, the hours that they put in, um
the SRO's, you know, the events that go
unnoticed where they're volunteering
their time to go spend time with our
youth. Uh the you know, I'll go to the
engagement office again on his own time
going in playing basketball uh with
youth like our officers are doing a
tremendous job.
Thank you. No further questions.
Thank you. council if I may.
She was going to speak. I just have I
have one question. Um I want to just
clarify on the the latest update of
statistics for use of force in the most
recent quarter that's available just to
put it in perspective. So that was the
slide and it's it's available on the
police website. Uh 86
8,698 arrests. Um, and the the use of
force on the continuum that's reportable
is 29. So, if my math's correct, that's
0.003% of arrest. I just wanted to make
sure that number is correct.
So, the
8,698 are calls for service with no
arrest. Got it. Got it. Yes. Uh, then
the next level up would be the arrest
not requiring force. Uh, followed by the
arrest reporting. Great. Force. Thank
you. I wanted to get clarification on
that. That's still 06% of the rest. So,
thank you. That's all council review.
Thank you, councelor Diaz. Um, thank
you, Chief Mendes, for the report.
Appreciate it. Um, couple questions. Uh,
regarding to one of the things you
mentioned was um after an incident
happens. Um, you mentioned the case law
that that occurred. what type of
coaching happens after or does any
coaching happen after when there's an
incident of what improvements could have
been made with the officer? Um I know
you said, you know, there's no Monday
morning quarterbacking, but uh are there
ways of coaching officers on alternative
approaches, etc. during an incident? So
Yan, when I was talking about some of
the um the the post uh review things
that we can do, coaching um and again
coaching is typically used um where they
didn't violate a policy, but we're
saying, "Hey, do better. You can do
this. This is a better option."
Um I I can think of one, you know,
coaching recently where we we like when
practical, um we tell to make sure they
know you're going you're under arrest.
tell them they're under arrest. Um we
had an officer not do that. Arrested the
person. We see that um they didn't do
anything wrong. The person was to be
arrested, but we coached them and said,
"Hey, like you had the opportunity to
tell them they were under arrest, that
needs to happen." Um now, if that
pattern were to continue with an officer
and and luckily it has not with that
officer, um then it would move on to
another level of discipline. Um thank
you. Um, and regarding the body cam, so
little I believe in 2018 is when uh we
first started having body cams or having
every officer uh wear body cams. Can you
tell us a little bit more about the
policy and the practice uh for our
police officers and body cams as far as
when they're turned on um and when the
footage is reviewed? Yes. So, we have a
we have a specific policy just geared
around body cameras. So, I would have I
didn't bring that with me to to really
get into it, but um it it's the it's on
all the time. Um we have a feature
activated on it where um I think it's
like up to 18 hours if they don't have
it on now that we can pull back and and
do it. So, those are some changes we
made recently with it. Um the
technologies has grown which now allows
us to do stuff like that, but um it
should be on uh when they're interacting
with the public.
That being said, again, we're humans, so
sometimes officers will be in the heat
and forget to turn it on. Um, that would
be a policy violation that gets
addressed through that means of the
policy.
Uh, and last question that I have is
regarding and sorry if I missed it, but
regarding the police social workers,
when are they typically engaged um
during interaction and what do those uh
uh situations typically look like? So,
they are not co-responders. Um, they
don't respond to the call. They do a lot
of um you know work beforehand. So they
they review the calls, they see the
patterns of the places we're going to.
They have a little bit more access to
some of the history with uh some of the
members in our community. So they will
do outreach that way. Um but they will
also, you know, if an officer requests
them, um officer gets to a scene, makes
it it's safe uh where they can enter um
and if it's a need for a social worker,
then they will respond uh to that. But
they're not they're not out there just
responding um before seems safe.
Um that concludes my question. Thank
you. Is there any other council members?
Um I'm going to go ahead and have Mayor
Sarra speak right now. Okay. Thank Thank
you. I just wanted to respond some of
the questions that came up. Thank you,
Chief. All right. Thank you. that um
have been raised. Um, so I'll just start
by saying that, you know, during my time
as mayor, uh, I did not always have full
trust for confidence in the police
bureau and nor did they and me. That has
changed. At least I know that I have
confidence in our police bureau and I
believe that we have made a lot of
strides. I'm proud of their work and the
work underway and that progress has been
a journey for short and I recognize that
some will support these e efforts and
some may not. Uh when I speak to
residents across the city I do hear a
clear message. They want a fully staffed
police bureau. You you are well aware
that we are down uh quite a number of
officers. Uh they want our officers
present in their neighborhoods and they
want safe streets. I want to clarify a
point of discussion. Um this has come up
from several of you related uh to
um a civilian review board. So just to
be perfectly clear, the city of
Lancaster has never had a civilian
review
board. Instead, um during my time as
mayor from 2018 to 2024, we have had a
community and police working group. Uh
this has not been a formal board,
commission or
authority. Um this group has played
played a valuable role in strengthening
those community relationships, informing
policy changes early on, identifying
leadership qualities for our new police
chief um and improving recruitment
strategies. They also have participated
in events like National Night Out
parties. You may have been you may have
seen them wearing t-shirts and over time
the the police bureau has
institutionalized community engagement
practices through the office of
community engagement and I think you
heard chief mention that. So last year
the working group merged with the call
toaction committee that's led by the
school district of Lancaster. Um that
group meets monthly with school staff,
youth serving organizations, city
representatives um from multiple
departments and others. An an area of
focus uh one area of focus is on youth
gun violence prevention and that um I
reported on to council in February
related to the PCCD grant that they
received through the city.
I have not supported establishing a
civilian review board because they lack
authority. Existing review boards in
Pennsylvania are purely advisory. Police
disciplinary processes are governed by
collective bargaining agreements just as
they are with every other union contract
in the city and across the state. Other
concerns include legal liability and the
fact that evidence in criminal cases
falls under the jurisdiction of the
district attorney's office and that
limits what can be shared
externally. If the goal is to build
trust between the community and police,
I do not believe a civilian review board
is effective. Without authority, they
create mismatched expectations between
the community, board members, and the
police bureau. However, I do see value
in external validation of police
policies and practices, and this is why
you've been hearing so much about the
accreditation process. It has been a
priority for me and Chief Mendes. This
was something that I have been wanting
to do since 2018. And under Chief
Menddees's leadership, we are getting
there. Uh, and you will continue to hear
more about this in the next month.
Regarding body camera footage, the city
strictly adheres to state laws governing
its release, including Act 22, the
Juvenile Act, and the Criminal History
Record Information Act. These laws
ensure the integrity of criminal
proceedings and the protection of
minors.
So, I understand community concerns
about police interactions with young
people. It is difficult to see youth
fighting in public parks and then be
pepper-sprayed. However, every
individual got home safely, and that's
something that we should not take for
granted.
Personally, as a mom, I will never
forget attending the funeral of a
16-year-old who was stabbed in June 2019
in a street fight. The anguish in that
church sanctuary stays with me. The
March March 2nd arrests were also
difficult to witness.
However, the individuals that were
involved broke the law, were repeatedly
warned, they fled from police, and they
were subsequently arrested.
Last Saturday, I received a video from a
personal resident, just a city resident,
of the same group on their bikes,
including one of the recently arrested
teens riding recklessly on Orange Street
near the exit of the Prince Street
garage, blocking traffic and surrounding
cars. Addressing unsafe behavior among
young bike riders is not about blame.
It's about recognizing a real issue.
Many residents have encountered this
group firsthand and express their
concern and their
frustration. If we all want our kids to
get home safely and to limit police
interactions with young people whenever
possible, then we need other
solutions. As such, we remain committed
to working with the school district,
Boys and Girls Club, Benchmark, the mix,
and others to foster those positive
relationships with young people. and I
encourage everyone to invest similarly.
I'll close with this. Your police bureau
and your city remain committed to public
safety in every neighborhood and on
every block. Public safety is a
partnership between the police bureau
and the community. Your bureau, your
police chief, who grew up in this city,
South Queen Street, and myself are
dedicated to that partnership and will
continue to strengthen it with city
residents who are committed to the same.
Thank you for the opportunity to add my
comments to the uh chief's report. And
that is all I have to say right now.
Thank you, Mayor Sarra. And I also want
to um extend a thank you for Chief
Mendes to take that opportunity to come
and give us the uh information and stats
of what is going on in our community in
reference to crime as well as
unfortunately children that are carrying
weapons that can cause damage not only
to themselves but others. And that right
now concludes everything for safety
committee. Thank you Amanda. Thank you
councelor Diaz. Uh we will move now to
our public works committee. Councelor
Hirs. Thank you, Council President. Uh
public works committee has five items on
the agenda tonight. Um they're all for
the most part administrative in nature.
Um council president, I may give a
minute for some folks, too. Sure. As uh
directors Campbell uh approach. Yeah, I
was going to say also favorite plural
way to say it.
Um, while while that's happening, could
I just uh follow up with councelor Diaz
about the funding that you mentioned,
counselor? Yeah, I did find it. Um, this
is a proposal from the Shapiro
administration to add $10 million uh to
the budget that is currently being
considered. Uh it would add money to the
special state fund that aids local local
governments facing severe economic
hardships in its proposed budget for the
202526 fiscal year. Um this would uh
help support communities under the
municipal financial recovery act also
known as act 47 uh which gives
municipalities that declare financial
distress um access to these resources.
So, um, it this is I'm reading from a a
news article from March 24th. So, it
sounds like this is in a budget proposal
from the Shapiro administration. And,
um, obviously we'll we'll pay attention
to that moving forward. Um, and I I'll
just say like it's very frustrating that
that money would only be eligible for
cities um, who are entering Act 47,
which we are not very much on purpose.
Correct. Yes, I agree. and I was looking
at the same. Thank
you, councelor Hirs. Yes, back to uh
public works. No, no, that was a good
that was a good
uh information to add in there. Um, and
it's all kind of uh related, I think, or
at least it was coming from the
conversation we were having earlier, um,
which is about, uh, upgrades to, um, our
water infrastructure. Uh so in relation
to resolution 27, I'll um I see director
Stephen Campbell at the stand.
Thank you very very much. Um I will
introduce the um the pieces that we're
we want to talk about in the following
way. The city has talked about some
about the Penvest loans recently. As a
reminder, Penvest is the Pennsylvania
State Revolving Loan Fund. They provide
funding for certain water, sewer, and
storm water projects. While they offer a
few grant options, most of their funding
is in the form of very low interest
loans. We pursue this funding in place
of bond funding as the projects qualify
to take advantage of the lower loan
rates.
On March
3rd, Tina Campbell mentioned that we
will be going after Penvest financing
for some sewer and water projects that
are eligible for Pennst. Penvest
requires resolutions for us to submit an
application. So, these resolutions
tonight are for the submission of the
application. They are not to accept loan
funding.
These applications will be submitted in
one of the penvest application cycles in
2025. There are three resolutions
regarding PENvest this evening, but they
relate to only two PENvest
applications. The first resolution this
evening
27-2025 is for the continued work on
lead line replacement. We are actually
pursuing some grant funding on this
application and we have to write the
application as a loan application but
there is grant funding available for
this work. So we are pursuing that with
this application.
The application for
27-2025 is in the amount of
1.709 338 million which represents
approximately
108 lead water service lines for
Lancaster city. This is these are the
lines that we've already identified and
or with a little bit of reconfirmation
need to be uh
uh reconfirmed. We do what we call
potholeing to make sure that they're
that they require replacement. That 1.7
represents approximately $6,000 to
$20,000 per line depending on the situ
the circumstance and be by going after
this lowinterest funding. We would
prohibit or we would make sure that the
property owner is not on the hook for
having to pay for that leadline
replacement. We are in the process right
now of having done approximately
identified approximately 25 to 27% of
the lead lines in the city of Lancaster
or of the lines in the city of
Lancaster. And we're about to uh have
what we call machine learning, an upload
of machine learning information within
the next couple of months that hopefully
would increase that percentage to about
75% of the 60 to 75% of the lines to be
known or not known. But over the course
of the next two to three years, we are
still going to be continuing to confirm
the inventory um of lead of lead of
service lines that need to be replaced
because they're lead or or
other. So this is this particular
request is to uh is to seek the ability
to make the application for the 1.7
million in in um lowinterest loans from
Penvest.
Thank you, Director Campbell. And I'll
just add um that you know part of the
confirmation process, Pennsylvania is
one of uh four states that is requiring
or the D in this case is requiring two
forms of confirmation. Correct. So
that's part of what adds to the
additional the cost and the constrnation
of having to do this work. Yes. Yeah.
Um, are there any public works committee
comments on resolution 27 or comments or
questions from full
counsel? Uh, council president. Thank
you. Um, Dr. Campbell, I I missed it. I
was trying to take some notes. You
mentioned that this would cover how
many? Approximately how much? About 108
service lines. Thank you very much.
That means the that means the
reconfirmation, the
excavation, the removal and the
replacement of those lines. Uh and there
we because we are pretty certain of
which which these lines are. We know
that some of them require a lot of
excavation. There's a lot of stone work.
There's a lot of and then there
replacement of the sidewalks etc. So
that you don't have an unfinished
situation when it's completed. And just
to put a finer point on it, the funds
would cover the total cost of that where
in other circumstances in other cases
outside of this project, property owners
would be uh responsible for the total
cost of the That is correct. Thank
you, Councelor. Uh thank you. Thank you,
Council. Thank you, Director Kim. Uh
what is the budgetary impact on this
additional debt service? the budgetary
impact on the lead service line
replacement. Yeah. On this on this loan
or this MS um this is this is perhaps
the the lowest way the lowest priced or
lowest cost way that we can get this
work done. It is a low interest loan. it
does need to be repaid but it is by
being a low interest loan over time uh
it minimizes or reduces the impact as
much as practical. Is that to say that
it eliminates it? No. There are there's
still a lot of work that still has to be
done to confirm over the course of the
next several years the number of lines
that do require replacement. Um and it
is a basically an unfunded mandate that
we need to find we as a municipality as
as every municipality in this country of
the United States has to find the ways
of replacing the lead service lines. Um
and as of the date uh a a date in early
or mid 2023 the cost of that is uh the
cost of of lines that are fall under
this mandate will not be borne by these
by the particular property owner. Uh
thank you. Uh and on the contrary does
that mean should we be getting more
should we be going after more dollars
through this? We are it's a very good
question and we've tried several
different ways of doing this. the there
are two challenges. One challenge is
that every time you make this
application uh or or in the earlier
programs there's a there's an
administration fee that attaches to
making that application. And so the the
higher number of applications we make,
we still have that same administration
fee applied every for every application.
So, we're trying to group them as much
as possible with ones we already know
and and hold off until the next batch uh
is knowable. And that's why it is
unlikely that we're going to go after
more funding like the lead service line
funding until the machine learning
information is uploaded because then
we'll have another critical mass of
numbers. Our hope is that at that point
we're not we will not be limited by
location in in the in the sense that the
earlier applications were based on what
they called neighborhoods um areas that
were in close proximity to each other.
We're hoping that we can just have a
collection of of lines that need to be
replaced irrespective of the
neighborhood that they're in which gives
us a lot more flexibility. It gives it
it allows it to be a less costly
endeavor. So, we'd be borrowing less
money to be able to perform more of the
work.
Oh, sure. Um, I just wanted to add that
um a piece of this as as director
Campbell mentioned um is uh that we are
actually looking for grant funding for
this. So, this is one of the few
programs that Penvest will offer grant
funding with. Um, and one of the things
that Penvest has uh has recommended is
that we look at specific neighborhoods
um because it helps us to increase our
um opportunities for grant funding. And
so some of the some of the reason that
this is the 1.7 million and not more is
because we're looking at some of these
concentrated areas that he was talking
about as well.
Uh, thank you and I appreciate your
guys' attention to this and I look
forward for more reporting to council on
how this goes. And that concludes my
question.
Thank you, councelor. Any other
questions from council council please?
Thank you councel. Uh thank you Lary
Campbell for the presentation and what
is the expected uh timeline for
receiving u funding and completing this
replacement? I don't know if I missed
it. No, you didn't miss you didn't miss
it and it's uh it's it's a couple of
questions. One, when we by applying for
this funding, we're hoping that the
information that the funds will be
available
by early
2026. Um we the the requirements of the
program are at this moment that all
lines must be identified and removed
within approximately 10 years. I that
has not yet changed but we understand
that there may be some changes in policy
under the current administration. Yeah,
that that has not changed, but that is
um a request that mayors are bringing to
the new administration um regarding that
time frame of 10 years. And I do want to
emphasize that the city of Lancaster has
had a this is a spam call that people
are just trying to get at me for. um
that uh the city of Lancaster has had a
program for lead service line
replacement for almost 15 years and
we've been replacing a certain a small
number of lead lines each year during
that period but with a mandate we have
to accelerate that program and it and
with that mandate which is unfunded we
we must find the ways of doing it as a
city not uh as had been done previously
and I just want to underscore that we
continue to treat our water to prevent
and lead leeching, which is in contrast
to other communities that have had lead
in their water um and have not followed
um the proper protocols to reduce and
eliminate lead bleaching. So, I always
just like want to underscore that. So,
this is a problem. And as you have all
heard me say before, we have more
exposure to children uh becoming
poisoned by lead through paint than we
than we do because they have a water
source.
[Music]
Thank you.
Thank you, councelor. Please. Any other
questions or comments from members of
council? Um from the public? Any comment
or question?
Hi. Okay, Darlene Bird, maybe council
kind of understands everything that's
going on, but as I come to these
meetings and I hear about these
resolutions, it makes me want to ask
more questions. At the last council
meeting, we approved to go for Penvest,
I think, for $9
million. Is that correct?
Uh, is that the extent of your comment?
No. 9.1. Yeah, it was 9.1. Thank you.
Okay. Also, we just talked about two
resolutions, number 25 and n and number
26, which totals like $5.6 million that
would be going into the water. And I'm
assuming some of these lead lines as
well. We are now applying for
$1 million. And um I heard uh Mr.
Campbell say it's a grant or a loan. I
don't think that was clear. I mean, I
would like to know if it is a grant or a
loan. What is the interest rate? How low
is it? I also understand that they're
going to be targeting neighborhoods. And
I know back when they first got the lead
uh got money to do the lead lines, they
targeted the southwest. And I remember
coming to council and questioning while
you're working on lead paint in the
southeast, why do you not focus in that
area to get rid of all the lead? So out
of these 108 homes that would get done
and they're targeting a neighborhood. Do
we know where that may be?
They're my questions. answer a couple of
those questions if you want me to. Um,
and I'm going to invite. So, part we
don't know if we're going to get a grant
or a loan yet, Miss Bird. We have to
apply. Okay. And there's a certain
amount of money that Penvest has through
the state revolving loan program. And
they um uh evaluate based on the
um uh criteria and need. And so that
goes to both the economic conditions in
a particular neighborhood as well as our
ability to identify that that that is
where lead lines are. There are fewer
known lead lines in the southeast than
there are in the southwest. That's why
we're starting there. Additionally, the
total um project over 10 years for lead
line replacement
um Director Campbell, Steve, I can't
remember, but we're in the we're above
$10 million of total. Where are we? I
can't remember. I'm sorry. We're
assuming it's going to be between 12 and
$15 million.
all all told total
um at that at the value of the dollars
in the respective years. Yes. And so
that that is why um we we don't know if
we're even going to get any grant
funding or if they're only going to
apply uh appropriate funds for a loan.
But we're just talking in for this
resolution. We are just talking about
lead line replacement. The previous
resolutions did not have to do with lead
line replacements. They had to do with
other infrastructure related to the 42in
main, the membrane replacements which is
the how to clean the water and the
treatment plants as well as the waste
water which is completely separate.
Those are two different things. And if I
may just add as well, since many of the
much of the utility infrastructure is
very very expensive, Penvest is the
lowest loan rate that we that we can go
after. Otherwise, we're looking at even
bond financing, which often is more
expensive over time. So, we we we try to
go after the funding that is least
costly in order to do the work that is
necessary. Right. That's why I didn't
understand why at the last council
meeting we just went for 9 million if we
knew we were going to go for from
Penvest I think they counted 9 million
in the budget if I'm correct. Why wasn't
we asking for more when we got two more
items and resolutions here and we're
paying administrative fees now for three
applications when we just submitted one.
I'll let Director Tina Campbell respond
to that. Um yeah, I'll just respond
quickly with that one. Um so the what we
approved at the last meeting was for
bond um funding. So that was for funding
that doesn't get um the the projects
wouldn't be supported by a Penvest. We
wouldn't be able to apply for them
because they're not um eligible for
PENvest funding. Um so that's what we
approved at the last one. And I included
9 million in that for PENve best. Um,
no. The what was approved was just the
was just the bond. Um, we talked about
um some PENvest funding that's coming
up. Um, but that has not been approved
or or applied for at this point. It's
not part of this. It's not part of this.
No.
Are there uh any other questions or
comments from the public?
Hello, sir.
Hello again. Uh Tony Dastro, 700 block
New Holland Avenue. Uh I don't have
concerns as it relates to the immediate
content of these, but just, you know,
I'm kind of reflecting on the bonds and
this work that we need to do right now.
Uh because ultimately these things
increase the cost of living in
Lancaster. In the long run, the debt
service obviously is incorporated into
our taxes.
Um the point or the thought running
through my head rather I'm not 100% sure
about this. I'm just saying it for
thought. Um you know I know the city at
times throughout the years has um
leveraged uh revenues from sewer or
water to help balance the budget. Um,
and maybe it's worth cuz like in the
charter we made it so you can't sell
utilities. Maybe it's worth keeping
those funds separate in the long run as
well. Uh, cuz you know, I don't think
anybody would have ever anticipated the
PAS situation, but maybe if water
revenues had never been touched over the
years, there would have been more to
pull from. Um, so I'm not saying that
it's like a solid I think but I think
it's worth looking into like keeping all
these funds separate for the long run so
that nobody throughout any of because
the this the debt situation for the city
is something that occurs over a long
period of time, not just any singular
person or council. Um so yeah that
that's just what's been going through my
head as we discuss this issue is the
idea of keeping uh sewer and water um
the their revenues separate and leaving
them to those departments um in part
because like one this is the a need of
life and you want to make sure the
money's there but two we have customers
outside of the city um so yeah those are
just some thoughts thank you Mr. Dastra,
um, why are you thinking? You don't need
to comment, but you've just created a $4
million hole in the budget in the
general fund budget that you would then
have to fill. Yeah, I'm not talking
about this year. I'm I'm saying long
long run.
And uh, Director Campbell, uh, just to
clarify point there, the the funds that
we use to pay for our water are our
property tax our property tax bill. It's
our water bill. Is that correct?
The funds that we pay for our water are
rateayers. Rate payers. So including
those non city res, right? So the the
debt service that for funds that are
borrowed to do capital work in the in
the water fund or the wastewater fund is
paid for by those rates. Thank you.
Any other questions or comment from the
public on this resolution 27? Yeah.
Um, just for clarification, the 42-in
main and membrane from the last
administration, was that ever replaced?
That's related to resolution 28. Yeah,
that's the next one coming up. The next
one. So, I'd be happy to speak to that
when we go over that resolution. The
mayor made a comment on it, so I'm
reflecting towards her comment. And she
was just about to answer. Was making a
point of order. Okay. Yeah, cuz she was
just going to answer and you're
interjecting. the lead of the chair of
public works. We'll address that in our
next res. Okay. The um 6,000 to 27,000
per line for uh the unit replacement. Uh
do you know what contractors were put on
these or is that the cities? Those will
be those will be competitively bid and
because there are uh currently residents
that are paying this amount because
there were some homes that were done uh
as far as the lead line and the
replacements and these homeowners were
affected by this cost and the city has
yet to offer any type of you know you
know anything to the homeowners. Mr.
Gomez, could I speak to your question?
Um I think part of this is to offer that
assistance um actually is to cover the
cost of these 108 so that it's not the
homeowner that is covering that cost and
also um yeah I'll just leave it at that.
Okay. But this has been ongoing
conversations. This is not something
that you're presenting as a resolution
today. There was $7.1 million that was
received from a grant for this issue.
That's different. or is the 9.1 along
with the 7.1 million added to this
funding that you're looking for? No. No,
this is something different. And this is
for the internal water service line
inventory which is still the inventory
is still taking place. There hasn't been
any replacement yet of the internal lead
service lines. Correct. Correct. Okay.
Thank you.
just just as a a reference, one may want
to look on at the list of projects
because it's very easy to confuse one
penvest application request with
another. Um there is a list of projects
I believe it's currently on
the the the project the list of projects
for which the capital budget is
supporting that we had submitted to
council in previous meetings that's
available I I can confirm where it's
available but I'll make sure that you
all know where it is so that a link can
be found so that one can take a look at
the the projects and the funding related
to each of the respective projects.
There are dozens of projects in water,
dozens of projects in wastewater, and a
few projects in storm water.
Sorry, I wasn't sure which list you were
talking about. That's actually um on our
budget page on the website, so you can
find it there. Yeah. Thank you.
Question or comment from the public on
resolution 27?
Hearing none, I will make a motion to
move resolution 27 to our full meeting
of council on April 8th. Second. All
those in favor? I
I Okay, then the second and third
Penvest resolutions relate to the water
main transmission line project that Miss
Gomez had mentioned. I've talked about
we've talked about this at both the
March 3rd and March 25th meetings and we
discussed this in more detail in the
fall as we talked about our capital
plan. This is a large project
approximately $41 million that is
required because our water main coming
from the Susuana water treatment plant
is way past its useful life and we must
have redundancy. This this main supports
over twothirds of our water customers
and this is the project that overlaid
the bond funding in the graphs that we
provided to you on both March 3rd and
March
25th. Penvest requires that a project be
shovel ready before we can apply for
financing for the project. This project
is still working through permits,
design, etc. And in fact, while we're
trying to be conscientious of the costs,
there have been some some adjustments
over the last several months that
confirmed less costly land acquisitions
as necessary because this is a a line
that needs to go from the Suscoan part
of it is the line that goes from the
Suscoana water treatment plant to the
Oyster Point Reservoir.
However, because of the deadline for a
$3 million grant that we have for this
project, as well as supply chain times,
we may pursue some interim bank
financing until the project can be
funded fully by Penvest. And if
necessary, uh, Director Tina Campbell
can speak to that. If we pursue this
short-term financing, Penvest requires a
resolution saying that our intent is to
write refinance the short-term financing
with them. This is the third Penvest
resolution. So the se the second Penvest
resolution is requesting permission to
make the application for the Penvest
investment and the third is for is
committing that we would pay for any um
short-term finance re
uh re that the intent is to refinance
the short-term financing and that we
would pay that.
Thank you Director Campbell. Um just a
quick question. Um so the interim
financing is that being pursued due to
the urgency of this particular project.
Part of it is to make sure that we have
several ready and can move from one
phase into the next phase without
several year interruption.
And is there an amount on that interim
that the city might seeking? That's 3
million rough amount.
That's the 27 million. Sorry, speak.
Yeah. So, that would be about 27
million. Um at uh we're not sure if
we're going to need to pursue the
interim financing yet or not, but it
would be mainly for um the the pieces of
equipment that are needed um or or um
actual pipe that's needed um that would
be supplied for the project.
And that that's that's critical at this
moment for several reasons, but the key
reasons are that if you if one does not
have the equipment or the material
available, everything comes to a halt.
The the potential for um for ch uh
supply chain interruption has been great
since the advent of COVID. It has
changed somewhat, but we may have
different challenges as we go forward.
But because it is a critical need, being
able to purchase or have the ability to
purchase the equipment and the materials
for
these 8 miles or so of of of
infrastructure would allow us to get the
work once the work gets started, we can
move forward without interruption.
Sorry, we're playing a little tag team
here. The um I just wanted I did just
want to add um Steve mentioned a $3
million grant. We do have a $3 million
grant for this project that's been
awarded. Um there's a deadline on that
funding. Um and so that is another piece
of this interim uh financing. We would
be able to p use that 3 million to
purchase some of this equipment. Um but
getting all of it is what we're looking
at at this point.
Thank you for that additional context.
Um, I'll open it up to questions from
full counsel and the committee, the
public works
committee. Council President, thank you,
Council H. Um, so we've been talking
about the large diameter waterway
replacement for quite some time.
Director Campbell, can you just briefly
talk about what phase we're in because I
know we've been phasing this project
because you mentioned it's eight miles
of infrastructure. There are three
phases and the numbering often gets
confusing. One phase is from the
Suscuana River to the Suscuana water
treatment plant. That's that's the raw
water bringing the raw water into the
treatment plant. The second part is
bringing water from the Suscuana water
treatment plant to the oyster oyster
point reservoir. That's the long
distance line. That's the steel line
that has its useful life. It's on paper
useful life ended quite some time ago
and we need to address that or else
there's the potential and I don't want
to I don't want to scare. We're not
scared about this but there's the
potential for a for a break that may
create major problems that we don't want
to to be dealing with as an emergency.
And that's why we were trying to do it
this way. And the third the third part
is from the reservoir to the
distribution system. Most of that part
has already been completed um or paid
for and and much of that is currently
underway. The the part from the from the
river to the water treatment plant still
needs some design and confirmation of of
sites for acquisition or for for playing
with. And then the the main part has
largely been designed, but we need to
complete the design so that it is
actually shovel ready and can be bid uh
for as appropriate.
Thank you. And I appreciate you saying
that there's not really cause for alarm,
but this is incredibly important that
it's getting done. Um, and I'm just to
kind of also encapsulate the amount of
work that this project t takes. I'm
assuming that there are endless permits
with you mentioned permitting with other
municipalities along the way uh rights
of way easements that sort of thing like
with every individual property owner
with with every with each usually with
most municipalities we're trying to use
existing rights of way to the extent
practical but sometimes it is private
property sometimes it is municipal
property in a variety of different
municipalities sometimes it's
negotiating with Amtrak or other federal
level infrastructure
um where we can share infrastructure,
share existing infrastructure, we can
usually keep the cost down somewhat. And
so where we could identify lines or or
infrastructure and rights of way that
can be shared, that's where we have
that's where we lean towards that's we
try to negotiate. Thank you. I just want
to take a moment to reorient us in the
project and also appreciate the amount
of work that has gone into planning to
get us to just this point.
Thank you, Council President. Uh,
councelor M. Uh, thank you, Council
Pers. Thank you, uh, Director Camp. Um,
councelor, uh, Council President, uh,
start kind of getting into the question
I was going to ask, but given that the
water is used by other municipalities,
um, are there any inter municipal
agreements that people could try to
negotiate where they could be putting up
some of the costs or I I I appreciate
some using some of the right to uh,
public right away. everything. Um, but
is there any way we could go to the
other municipalities and say, you know,
can you help support this project in X
way or the we're going to raise rates
for other municipalities by X amount. So
in principle, yes, the the rates are
different for outside outside city
customers than they are for inside city
customers. But it is one water system,
one water utility which is a little bit
different in concept than the wastewater
which we are we share with a v variety
of partners and we need the consent of
each partner every time we're doing
infrastructure that affects the whole.
But in this case, we would we try to
find the the most effective,
cost-effective,
uh least annoying way to get the work
done. And then it is a a different rate
is charged to the in internal rate
payers than it is to the out external
rate payers.
Thank you. And I appreciate that. Uh I
just I I would hope that the city isn't
taking the majority of the burden. I
understand we own the infrastructure and
it's a city asset, but um I do feel that
other municipalities should be stepping
up and paying their fair share as well.
So whether that's through rate changes
through the PUC or whatever it may be, I
I think it's important that we think
about that for the future. We do work
through the PUC, it needs to be PUC
approvable in all in all aspects,
whether it's external or internal rate
payers. Um we this is one reason it
often takes as long as it does because
we try to be as cost-effective as
possible and we explore
uh alternatives that it may be costly to
do the engineering to explore the
different alternatives but it hopefully
reduces the actual capital costs to all
parties involved.
That concludes my question.
Thank you council. Uh council please
thank you for the question just a quick
question and what impact what financial
impact there is any uh on the water
rates for city residents for the
waterways rates for the
rates this is part
of the presentations we've made over the
last several months where the city of
Lancaster
is about to undertake some major
investments. Partly because of aging
infrastructure, partly be in order to
meet the requirements of the lead
service line replacement, which is an
unfunded mandate, partly because of the
vagaries of addressing POS, the forever
chemicals, and their prevalence in our
in our water system.
In addition, we're looking at leak
detection so that we are reducing the
amount of water, treated water that we
pay for um that is escaping through
leaks into the soil. Um there's a lot of
capital projects that we described both
in the fall and in the and in the recent
presentations that address a lot of
these concerns. For better or for
worse, this 40 some odd million dollar
investment
[Music]
is in this in the scope of the larger
investments that we're about to
undertake over the course of the next
several
years in the moderate range and it's
part of our what we call our our our
ongoing restoration and and and
investment work. um whether we had a
consent decree for wastewater or not,
whether lead service lines existed or
not, whether POS existed or not, we
would have to replace these
lines. Um or else have
risk an impingement on access to clean
water in our water system. And we're
supplying water for 150,000 people.
So it is not an
immodest
expense. It is an impactful expense and
it is a necessary expense, but it is not
the most it's not the highest expenses
that we're likely to encounter over the
next several years,
but it will impact um I mean it will um
have impact on the water rates for the
residents anyway, right? Yes, it will.
Both internal and external rateayers.
And this reimbursement
will will it affect the city's overall
debt or
Yes, it will. Do you want to speak to
that, Tina? Yes. Yes, it will. But do
you want to talk to how it will?
Yeah, it's a it's a it is a loan. So, it
would be a part of the overall um city
debt um focus on the water fund.
Council, I think I saw a question.
Thank you, Council. Just make sure I'm
connecting the dots here and
piggybacking off of Council Med's
question. Um just to clarify uh city
rateayers are disproportionately paying
for this because the debt is paid by
repairs water repairs or yes please
because it's a it's a calcul no um so
the how how the uh water rates work is
that we do need to go to the PUC for any
rate for any rate increases outside of
the city. Um, so we uh ha I don't want
to get into too many details of of PUC
rate cases. We're we're going for a PUC
rate case now. So we're looking to
increase external rates, not not
internal rates at this time, or at least
that's the the hope. PUC may require us
to increase internal rates, but our goal
is to um to look at external rates at
this time. Um once you put in a PAC rate
case, you have to wait another 18 months
at least in order to put in another one.
Um and and projects need to be completed
um before the PUC will consider them to
increase the rate. And so our our goal
with timing of this is to be able to put
in a another PUC rate case as soon as
this project is complete. Um so that
external um customers would also see
that increase um at that time. So, so we
proact or we look at rate increases
considering these projects and the debt
cost of that and the rate increases for
both internal and external CL. Correct.
Correct. Yeah. Thank you for that
clarification.
Are there any other questions from
council or public works
committee? Any questions or comments
from the public? Yes.
Just to be sure, are we talking
about Angie? Are we talking about both
resolution uh 28 and 29? Is that correct
or are we just talking about 20? Sure.
Okay. So, we're talking about two. Okay.
So, um I think council, I think you're
all asking the right questions. I do
believe that no one's trying to say this
is not a need. We understand the water
and sitting on home room can explain a
lot to me. So, I do have a clear
understanding about that. The question
is how we're financing it. And that's
what council needs to be a concern
about. And Councilman Lashard, I
appreciate you're asking the impact on
the residents because that's what
council needs to be concerned about.
We're talking about borrowing 27 million
that we will pay back on bonds that we
already approved. If and I understand
the process that we need to have this
work shovel ready, then that means we
jump the gun to borrow the money on the
bonds because this process has to happen
first. And that's what council needs to
be looking at because one of the things
are we understand we already approved
the bonds but now to say we're going to
go get another loan for 27 million just
so we can be ready to spend the money
that we get from the bonds so that the
project shovel ready and then we're
going to take the money that we get from
Penvest I guess and the bonds and pay
this 27 million back. So, this is going
to be like a short-term loan, but in the
process, we're paying interest on that.
So, I think council needs to get into
the financing and not look into who's
saying we need this water line and
everybody understands the storm water.
Everybody, well, maybe they don't
understand it, but the need is there. We
know the city is old. We understand the
EPA. We understand what's going on with
our water. But the fact that our water
rates and things are going to go up is a
result of council approving borrowing
money when it's sitting and we're not
using it and we're paying interest on
it. Now we're this week we're talking
about getting a loan on the money that
we just borrowed to put us in more debt.
So, I think, you know, you need to make
sure that you understand exactly what
we're doing because this is a greater
impact on the homeowner and the
taxpayer.
If I could just say I I hear your
concerns and frustrations, Miss Bird. I
think that the way that this is set up
is that we have to borrow the money,
spend the money, put the projects in the
ground, and then go for a rate increase
to then pay ourselves back. And when we
go to the PUC, we are never I don't
think ever have gotten 100% of what
we've requested. And so it is an upside
down process. Uh and that is something
that you know we have talked about uh in
terms of effectuating change at the
state level with how the PUC
um does but they are also there as a uh
means of protecting rateayers
specifically those that do not have a
who are not represented by city council
who live outside of the city. So they
are there specifically to prevent any
kind of price gouging or uh raising of
rates unfairly. But the rule the rules
are the rules and we have to spend the
money first before we can get the rate
increase which goes to your point about
where are we borrowing this money from
and how are we how are we expeditiously
getting the projects in the ground and I
think those are the questions that
continue that council should continue to
ask especially because we're going to be
putting timelines um for projects on our
capital plan that we'll be presenting to
you in June and so those are the things
that you should be monitoring ing
because the bond funds I will say very
clearly historically the city has not
been good about getting projects in the
ground utilizing bond funds and that's
been a legacy that has been from you
know previous administrations that we
are trying to change and part of that
starts with having a capital plan and a
really clear sequence of what we need to
borrow for what projects and in what
sequence and not taking off not biting
off more than we can chew. because the
list of projects that was originally
presented was much longer than the one
that you got.
Thank you, Mayor. Is that fair? That's
very fair. Thank you, Councelor Hirs.
Yes. Related to that and and Director
Camp, you can just confirm,
additionally, PUC raid cases take a long
time. It's my understanding that from
the time you actually request a rate
case, it's it's typically about 9 months
to maybe not get all that you would ask
for. So I imagine that that planning is
also that just makes the planning all
that more difficult and also projects to
get done even more timely. So yes, it's
the the timing is critical not only in
terms of getting it started and
completed, but in order for us to
anticipate the the next borrowing, if
it's a subsequent phase to get done,
that work needs to get done within the 9
to 18 months that it may take for that
approval.
Thank
you. Are there any other questions or
comments from the public?
Yeah. So I understand that the PUC have
deadlines and their projects need to be
completed. So because we can't meet the
deadlines because projects are not being
completed, this is where we are. Um
there are you mentioned 150,000 people
that are accessing this water.
There's about 60,000 people in the city
of Lancaster as
residents. What measures are you using
to pursue the townships and counties
that are receiving water from us?
Because we should not be the only ones
held accountable to pay this. Like are
you have you sent out requests? Have you
sent out any type of uh formal made
meetings with the townships to um bring
in bring forth any type of revenue on
their part? Oops.
Sorry. It's a very fair question, but
it's the nature of a PUC. The public
utility commission establishes for our
water system not only the rates but the
the means by
which infrastructure uh investment can
be re can be compensated or reimbursed
and we cannot make changes to those. We
have to work alongside and within the
limits of the PUC limit or requirements
and legal limitations. It does, as the
mayor had indicated, allow for the the
reimbursement, which is via the rate
increases that take place independently.
There's rate increases at the exterior
which we've proposed for this year for
the exterior rate payers which is
hopefully going to be paying for part of
that interest for what we borrow in the
short term until it gets installed and
and accepted at which point the PUC
after the 9 to 18 months can say yes
that is approvable and therefore
uh reimburseable and then we would enter
into either another rate case for inside
rate payers and or outside rate payers
as well. So, it is kind of a seessaw.
Um, but to your point, we're we're
within the limits of and we're run by
the PUC, the regulations of the PUC in
terms of of how we access money from
outside. But it's a very very good
question, a very important question to
the conversation. Yeah, I have another
question. Sure.
Okay. Um the other question is
uh when you um when you just for the
record is the public works committee
present today because you keep
mentioning that like who is on the
public works committee? Is it just Mr.
Campbell? It's myself, councelor Diaz
and councelor or sorry I'm looking at
public safety council and councelor
Diaz. So three of us are present. Yes.
Okay. And how many are in the committee?
Just the three of you. Just the three of
you. Okay. Y and then um you had
mentioned uh you were going to refy the
first short-term financing. Are you
saying that there is already a loan in
place that you're looking to request or
pursue this funding to refinance what is
already in place? Can you clarify that?
Um so the short-term financing would be
as as needed. Um and that would be
refinanced to the PENvest loan which is
the administration resolution number 28.
Um once that Penvest loan is ready to be
um to be funded. Yeah.
So it is already No.
Can if you have a question you just ask
it in the in the mic. No, she answered.
Oh, she doesn't have a question. Okay.
Are there any other questions or
comments from the public?
Hello. Um Diane Desmond. I live off
Route 30 near the state police. Um I
wanted to just give you a little bit of
scope of um what I'm currently dealing
with in my apartment community. Um, we
saw from 2020, uh, sorry, from 2024 to
2025 a 67% rate increase on our water
bill. Um, and I'm not going to blame all
of that on these very necessary projects
because I understand that that could be
price gouging from my apartment complex.
However, um just because there was such
a drastic rate increase and that's
something that we like directly feel in
our pockets, what range of increase
should we as um citizens anticipate for
these projects and when do you predict
we may see those increases hit our
bills? Could you just say your name
again, please?
Diane Desmond. Miss Desmond, thank you
for your question. I actually don't
think you're a city of Lancaster water
customer. Oh, good. Okay.
Sorry. Yeah. I think just from where you
described where you live. Yeah. I'm like
right next to the state police. So,
yeah. I Yeah, we do not serve that area.
Okay. Thank you. Yeah. And there's a
water distribution map that's on our
website that you can just check your
address. But thank you so much. I think
that's right.
Any other question or comment from the
public? on resolution 28 or resolution
29. Uh hearing none, I'm going to have a
motion to move these together to our
full meeting of council on April 8th.
Second. All those in favor? I
um thank you so much. The only thing I
just want to say about, you know, it
it's not um lost on us what the impact
is going to be um to customers. And I
think that's why, you know, I'll just
speak from my perspective as someone
that works in in government finance. Um
a lot of it comes down to figuring out,
okay, where are the funds? What are they
eligible to be used for? And you kind of
have to game them in a certain way um to
get the best outcome. And I think part
of this process is, you know, we're
issuing bonds, but then we're also going
for a PENvest loan, which my
understanding is we can finance that at
a lower rate. Uh, director Tina camel's
waving her head, yes, than, you know, a
bond. And then we also have grant
applications, which actually is what
we're going to get into now. But I'm
only just emphasizing to say that it's
it's a capital mix. There's a mixture of
different funding sources that are going
into each of these these projects.
Um but with that I do want to talk about
these uh grants. So uh Director
Campbell, do you want to talk about
resolution number 30? Yes. Resolution
number 30 is authorizing the filing of
an
application for funding through the
Department of Conservation and Natural
Resources, DCNR. That's a state entity
community conservation partnership
program in the amount of
1.38535 million. I'm not sure if if what
you have says 900,000 or 1.385 million
but I have as of actually no I think we
got an updated one in the second email.
Yes. Okay. So the 1.385 is the is the
correct one. We anticipate that this is
for Southoun Park. We anticipate that
South End Park will cost approximately
$2.7 million total. DCNR limits us to
asking for
50%. And that's what the what the
request is for here. We're anticipating
um the match being from local partly
from local shares which we've applied
for separately under to the tune of
approximately $1 million. Um it is there
is a proviso since we're just making an
application. There's a chance that we
don't get all that we've been asked for
or that we're asking for. They would
tell us if we're not going to be
eligible for the full amount and we
would have be able to consent to either
accepting the lower amount or not doing
the project or changing the project all
together. But this this is asking for
permission to make the application.
Thank you, Director Campbell. Um and
I'll just add it's written in the
resolution text um what some of these
improvements will be. They include
upgrades to play command surfaces,
multi-purpose field, um basketball court
upgrade, improved EDA access, water
plane, fencing, improved lighting and
seating. Um it's just some of the things
that we hopefully will see happening at
South Park soon. And I will say that
this is one of the mo more creative um
endeavors that we've done recently. Um
partly as a result of the parks and
recreation open space master planning
process, but then separate consultants
that worked with the community in
different ways than we've worked with
them in the past where people's ideas
were were pasted together. There's
actually a a small uh skating skate park
as well as a roller park for for small
bicycles etc. So they've been able to to
maximize the utility of the south end
park for active recreation as well as
passive recreation.
Thank you. Um I'll open it up to
question or comment from the public
works committee or full
counsel.
Anything from the puddle?
How big is the south end?
That's a very good question. I'm not
sure.
Um do do you know where it is?
It's it's it ended up being a little bit
larger than we expected based on the
setbacks on the site as well as um
vegetation that could be relocated uh to
be able to make use of active recreation
and and this skate park
area, but I can get you this the
precise and and in fact it's on the
engage Lancaster website
says 1.2 2 acre park. That's about
right.
1.2 acre. What we're
1.2 acres.
It's not Oh, correct. It's It's not a
huge park. It's certainly nothing like
reservoir or Muser or Buchanan, but we
are able to pack a lot of in very
interesting activities in even that
small an area.
And then my other 1.38. Do you want to
come to the
Sorry, you should sit right there.
So the 1.38 is for both the south end
and Reservoir Park or just
Okay. And how much is it for the Oh,
we're not talking about that one yet.
Okay. Okay.
Then I can just
Okay. Yeah. So I could just mention um
you had mentioned the people's ideas uh
are in order to cut uh waste or cut
funding or try to save um as much are
you using uh
city residents, workers, skilled
workers, that Stevens um you know
uh people that are
actually in you know in the city that
can do these for less costs uh in terms
of looking for contractors, biders
because it's been known that um we're
wasting a lot of money and funding on
taxpayer dollar to recruit outside of
the city of Lancaster to do these
projects which take time because
commuters don't have the time to get in
here at 6:00 a.m. 7:00 a.m. to start
projects and we see them leaving at 3:30
p.m. when they should be leaving at
normal business hours. So, um, for these
projects as a whole and as a a city, you
know, can we can you um have some type
of consideration to utilize the
residents of the city of Lancaster who
are in training in Thaddius Stevens
graduates, you know, um, skilled
workers. There's multiple skilled
workers. We took pride in our city uh,
when we built and been here 30 years.
The residents have always taken pride in
their city, in community parks, in
upgrading, in cleaning, and doing
everything. We we're seeing more
outsiders coming into our city that are
costly. It's very cost effective. A lot
of them don't pay taxes here. you are
burdening the residents on these
projects that we can cut costs on. And
it's shameful that we continuously have
to go outside of the city of Lancaster
with 50 60,000 residents and say that
there's no one here that can take this
bid for a cheaper price. It it's it's
not fair. You know what I mean? We take
pride in building our city. It's always
been like that since the 50s, 40s, you
know, use the people here so that these
costs can be substantiated le or
lessened. I'm just asking for
consideration.
Well, as you may know, we do have a
relatively extensive self-performance
part of our work. Much of our paving is
self-performed. we can perform 34 to 50%
more paving because we self-perform
rather than contract out as a value
engineering effort. Um we can look at
what parts of any of the parks whether
it's this park or any park that we're
looking for funding for can be done as
self-performance. It does not mean that
self-performance is done without without
any expense. It does mean a different
level of of administration,
oversight, of purchasing materials, etc.
Um, but generally speaking, parts of
projects can be done as
self-performance. The challenge with
working with with uh working with uh
Thaddius Stevens or with other or
organizations is putting in place a a
longer term program which is not off the
table but a long-term program that not
only supports skill sets but skill sets
that that are transferable into their
workforce work experience as well. Uh,
as you know, Fatty Stevens currently has
a design and work program where the
students actually build affordable
housing in different parts of the city.
That's where they they're supervised by
journeymen or journey people who are
overseeing the work to ensure that it
meets the construction and designing
construction standards of the building
industry. Um it often
is there are there are trade-offs in
doing it that way, but there some of the
trade-offs may be appropriate
trade-offs. Um, but I think I take your
point that if if we're not able to find
not only if we're not able to find uh um
local contractors, but if the costs are
excessive or if we're not getting all
the funding that we're looking for and
we still want to perform this park,
that's those are options that we can
look at. Joe Jackson Park, for instance,
is an example where we're more more
likely to do most of that park with our
own source resources in order not only
to keep the cost down, but also to stay
on on a schedule that's accelerated.
Thanks for that additional context,
Director Camp. I'm glad you mentioned
the houses that Stevens uh students
built because I just passed the one they
are building currently on Hillside AB
the other day and um you remember when
that came to us and to see it get built
it's uh it's name um are there any other
questions or comments from the public on
resolution
30 hearing. I'll make a motion to move
resolution 30 to our full meeting of
council on April 8th.
said all those in favor I I
and then last and possibly least this is
the a request for an application for
funding through through again DCNR for
uh community conservation partnership in
the amount of
74,960 and I'm hoping that you had that
amendment as well um to be used for the
master planning of Reservoir park. We we
expect the master planning effort to be
approximately
$150,000. This is a 50% grant request
and we fully expect that that will be um
be able to come through. But the request
is for us to have the permission to make
the application.
Thank you, Director Campbell. Are there
any uh question or comments from public
works for council?
[Music]
The request is for
74490 960 rather and the total cost is
anticipated at
149. Uh thank you council. Uh director
Campbell thank you uh for your remarks
and just real quick question. Uh this is
for the master plan. This isn't for the
actual improvements. That is correct. So
the nature of master planning is that it
means reaching out to the community
which has been as I understand it and
please correct me if I'm wrong has been
hungry for this work to be done for
several years anyway but things have
changed throughout the city. It it's
also the best probably best location for
fairground park. Uh it has not only very
mature trees, but it also has uh a
subsurface a substrate that allows for
playground equipment and for carnival
equipment on a temporary basis. It's
also part of the East End community
small area plan. So there's ideas that
are being generated in terms of what the
recreational needs are for this
particular community in in large um as
well as trying to be consistent with the
the parks and recreation master plan
which identified
local neighborhood and regional needs to
be to be met. So, it's an opportunity
for reaching out to the community,
engaging them hopefully in in as dynamic
a manner as we have with the with
Southoun Park and others so that it can
address the the concerns and the needs
that are addressed that need to be
addressed today, not in the last parks
and recreation master plan. Thank you.
Thank you, Council M. Uh any other
questions or comments from
council from the public on resolution
31?
I just want to agree with um Mr.
Campbell when he said about the needs
changing and I'm wondering if we're not
jumping the gun on Reservoir Park as far
as we're planning because as you know
the county prison is going to become a
different place and a different site.
So, what will the need be for Reservoir
Park when that happens? And are we
willing to go back and reinvest more
money and to come up with a plan now for
$1.49 million, which is just a plan,
knowing that there's going to be other
changes. One of the things I want to
encourage council is there is no such
plan for a park in the southeast area.
And I think if we're going to talk about
putting a park, we have this location
behind Jackson Middle School where the
community has engaged and has spoken
loud and clear. That's what we would
like to see there, a park. And we're
just looking for council to come up with
a plan to say, well, let's see what we
can do here. I mean, we keep hearing
we're spending millions and millions of
dollars in the parks. We do have some
top lots in the southeast area, but we
do not have a park in the southeast
area. So, I just say don't jump the gun
for Reservoir Park and you're planning
on what it's going to be like because as
the county prison comes on that whole
block, that need may change and we don't
want to invest in something and then
we're turning around and borrowing more
money or seeking other grant money to
change it. Thank you.
Thank you, Mr.
Yeah, and I just want to piggyback on
that because I have been asking the
mayor since she first took this position
um that my concern was Reservoir Park.
We talked about this in the beginning of
her becoming mayor. Um
so there are
specifically, you know, things such as
the playground. So, I don't know if it
was seven, eight years that she's that
you have been mayor, but I've been
asking for the playground, and I know
it's not going to cost $1 something
million just to do the playground. The
pool is okay. I don't know what's uh
going to happen with taking away, you
know, what was there, which was the uh
arena. Um the the hockey uh arena, it
was dismantled completely. It could have
been used for something else like the
children playing baseball, you know. Um
they they they there's teams that are
associated with schools and they don't
have a turf to play in. You know, I
think Reservoir Park would have been
excellent because there was stools
there. I mean, there was um you know, it
was a whole hockey arena. All you had to
do was basic improvements. to take it
down completely is depriving the
children from usage and it's just
sitting there for years with nothing.
It's just an empty space. So I
understand that. Um did he you said 1.49
49 million for reservoir 149,000
149,000 that plan for 140 you said
150,000 um do you have specifics like
you were very specific hurse when you
said the basketball field you know when
we were talking about the southbend park
you were very specific can you um give
me specifics on what the 150,000 would
be for on Reservoir Park the design
so this is a master planning effort.
It's not the design effort. The master
planning effort means reaching out to
the local community, to adjacent
neighbors, to others who may may use the
park for whatever reasons they might
want to and identify what is in of
interest to them. What are the space
requirements for that? What are the
noise implications of some of that? Um,
are there aspects of the of the parks
and recreation open space master plan
that need to be recognized because it
because it is such a centrallylo park in
in principle um because it has special
characteristics such as being available
as a fairgrounds type park where no
other park in the city has that
availability without making major
damage. How does one make use of that?
And so similar to the processes that got
us from uh conception to more detailed
design for South End Park and others. It
would be inviting the community at
whatever level to come in and describe
what's important to them, what's
interesting to them. Hopefully it would
be a series of meetings so that people
can share their ideas and the and
consultants would come back several
times to say this is what we heard you
say. Is this what you what you actually
mean and how do we put something that
takes up this kind of space which might
be a ball field adjacent something that
be a skate park if those are the types
of things that in consensus that
community believes are appropriate. So
the master planning effort is to is to
generate the ideas as you're as you're
talking about because you've presented
several different ideas and many other
people may have other ideas as well that
they think may be appropriate for them
and their their own families. But it
would not be the specific design. It
would be making sure that here are
programmatically ways that these kinds
of spaces can fit in this kind of a
location. I do want to say that it will
be done a bit later in the process than
the anticipated schedule for the for the
south end for the east end
um small area plan in the sense that
that's currently underway. Um and so
some ideas may still be generated from
that which would be able to be talked
about on the table but not be ruled by
it. the c the city p the prison is a
county site and what we want with the
and maybe I should ask Chris to speak
but what we're hoping is going to happen
with the east end uh small area plan is
community- based ideas on what can and
should happen at that site that might
influence decision-m at the county level
whereas Reservoir Park is ours and
that's something that we can be making
decisions on rather sacros sacrosanked
within the limits of that park.
And um when we think about the southeast
plan um we are aware that the prison and
reservoir is in the southwest. Correct.
So when we're asking for a plan for the
southeast of Lancaster, we're not
talking about the southwest. I mean
every if you look at every quadrant you
have a plan for the city reservoir and I
think the plan that I saw on the
southeast plan includes reservoir res um
the prison and then some of the
southeast area. So it's both southwest
and southeast.
Are there other questions or comments
for the public on resolution 31? I just
want to say one thing. Sorry. Just real
quickly just to um uh and as far as
plans in Reservoir Park, um and
and you know getting the folks involved
and the residents, I've been living
there for 30 well 20 something years.
I've bought my house in 99. So I want to
make certain that we are very the
community in Reservoir Park area. We're
very informed. We have a neighbors uh
engagement, you know.
Um it's a it's it's all we're we're very
active together. So, we know what we
want. We've been stressing our opinions
um for quite some time. So, it's not
like, you know, we don't know what we
want and it's been shared with the mayor
to uh like primarily the park itself
because they opened it up to
um I don't want to
say how do you without offending anyone
offenders ch child offenders live there
in the houses that is close by Reservoir
Park and they come into the park and
they do things and they leave things
that we continuously have to clean up
and they write all over that. It's it's
old. The the playyard is old. It needs
to be re reconstructed. So, that was our
major concern for the last 8 years. They
put in a pool. They put in um the wheels
uh the bike wheels. Uh, I mean there's a
lot of improvements in the park, but as
far as maintaining that park, you know,
fixing the grass, adding, you know, the
beauty in the the park, it's not being
done. We we we as a community, we have
to do it ourselves, even if it's
cleaning up stuff on the floor. Um, so
yeah, we we are just more concerned
about um picking up a needle when our
kids are going down a slide and making
sure that it's cleaned
um and and maybe taping up uh cracks
within the
actual set, the play the play unit set
and um yeah, so it's safe for the kids
to go down. So it's it's old. It needs
replaced.
Tony Dastra, 700 block of New Holland
Avenue. Um, I don't have a problem with
us approving the grant application. I
think it's worth applying for and seeing
where it goes. Um, but I do think that
Miss Bird is making a good point about
parks in the Southeast in general. I
think Miss Gomez is as well. Um, you
know, and I want to just kind of maybe
say a good thing is we could potentially
use this program to fund those sort of
parks in the future. Um, so I, you know,
I think it's worth the city applying for
the grant. I do also have some level of
reservation because of the planning that
needs to occur with the prison. Um, but
I understand you're working from the
frame of reference you have right now
and I think this is a very reasonable
thing to do.
Thank you, Mr.
D. Are there other comments or questions
from the
public? Hearing none, I will make a
motion to move resolution 31 to a full
meeting of council on April 8th. Second.
All those in favor? I I
And that concludes the public works
committee. Thank you very much. Thank
you, councelor Hirs. Uh we will now go
to the community planning committee.
Councelor Craig. Thank you, Council
President.
Um, community planning has one item on
the agenda this evening. It's
administration bill number
325 authorizing the sale of real
property. And that's me, councelor
Craig. Thank you. Um, currently uh
the ordinance sets forth how we are able
to sell property uh in the city of
Lancaster and that is through two
options. either by sealed bid or through
public auction. Uh this uh uh
administrative bill uh three would
authorize the sale of real property
through a third method which is through
a licensed real estate broker. Um, and
so I would call your attention to the
section in the ordinance that specifies
that um, if we were to do this that
council would um, approve the process
uh, for how to select the real real
estate agent, etc., etc. So, that I
believe is spelled out um, in the
ordinance that was provided to council.
So this is really a way that we can
utilize our home rule status uh to
effectuate change uh to make more
efficient how we do certain things and
um that's the gist of this uh bill in
front of you for consideration.
Thank you mayor. I'm curious to know
what was the the process before was that
we would do a resolution
and go over the
resolution and go from that instead. And
then once Simply got into um home rule
the beginning of January, that allowed
us the ability to change the the
narrative, so to speak. Um the way that
we did it before was always council
approved the sale of a property. Uh what
this leg piece of legislation is doing
is not changing that. what it is doing
is adding a method for how we can sell a
piece of property that council proves to
be sold. Um, home rule. The thing that
changed about home rule is that it gives
us some flexibility where we don't uh
where we where we're able to have
flexibility to sell real property. And
that can now include using a real estate
uh agent, which means that it's the
property gets listed on an MLS listing,
that more people see it, that other
realtor can talk to their clients about
projects that they're working on and not
just rely on an ad in the Sunday paper
that says that we're accepting bids.
Excellent. Thank you. So, we'll have a
wide range of people that are available
or that could be available to purchase.
Yeah. that will know about the property
being for sale. Thank you. Um, are there
any questions from the committee?
Council Craig
if Mayor Saraji, uh, would council still
um have to approve the methodology if a
there was a property um that the city
wanted to sell um or is that up to the
administration to determine which route
they want to go uh to sell the property?
I it is my understanding and I have to
actually go back and check um I have to
read it again because I read it a day
ago and I'm just not sure that I'm $100.
But what I think is that when we bring
to council uh property or or want to
change how we have a property for sale,
we would need to get council's approval
for this method and then there's a
process for how we're selecting realtor
and all of that stuff.
I think it'd be great just for the next
meeting if we could just have that
clarification. I think it's in the
ordinance. If you read the ordinance, I
think it's there. I'm just I haven't
read it in a day, so I don't want to
misspeak. Thank you, mayor.
So, currently, I mean, the way it's it's
read here, I think it's
number three, it would provide
compensation to be paid to the real
estate broker. Is that what we're doing
currently? Or it says the addition to
um I'm trying to find it in the list of
17 attachments. One second. Um it's
right after section right below section
one. Yeah, I have to find the Oh, thank
you, Chris. A handout. Yes. Um so right
now we're not paying a real estate
broker because we can't use a real
estate broker. Exactly.
Did I did that answer your question,
councelor Diaz? So why would we? So but
right here it's stating that
by changing it the person will be able
to negotiate and we would have to
compensate the real estate agent is that
or broker. Yes, we would pay a real
estate broker for their work for their
services. Currently we do the same. No,
we ain't doing that. currently were
procluded from using a real estate
broker. Exactly. Thank you very much.
That's what I needed to know. Council
Greg, may maybe this would help as as
well. T and mayor, typically uh realtors
get paid once the sale of the property
is complete. They're not paid prior to
correct.
Yeah. So, I would imagine that would
happen in this this situation.
So it u upon recommendation of the
mayor, city council may by resolution
authorize that specific parcels of real
property be sold through the use of a
licensed real estate broker. So that we
would be bringing to you a resolution
that would authorize the use of a real
estate broker. That resolution must
authorize the same which would provide
the terms, conditions and basis uh which
is uh point number one. Number two,
provide who has authorization to
negotiate an offer and accept an offer
submitted to the city. Uh three, I'm
paraphrasing here, provide for the
compensation to be paid to the broker
and require require reporting to city
council is number four. Um and five, set
forth the time frame during which offers
of sale may be solicited for such
property by the licensed real estate
broker. So all of this would be part of
a of a resolution that would come to
council when we wanted to use a realtor.
Are there any further questions from the
um council as a whole?
Thank you, councelor Craig. Um, I know
this is the first reading that this is
just a committee, but um, I mean, I do
have some some questions around what the
process would look like, the selection
of the realtor and um, you know, also I
I understand it would expand the um,
possible market for a property to be
sold. Um, but I I mean, I do think that
there might be I mean, real estate is
very competitive market. Um, and I I
just have some questions
around how we decide which realator, you
know, that would be and I know I
maybe these are some questions we can
talk about at the next meeting as well,
but yeah, I I will say that like the
redevelopment authority of the city of
Lancaster has a realer. Um, the board
hired them. Um, and I can we can find
out more information about that process.
I I think that this is step one and then
there would be a follow-up step that I
mean we would certainly bring back to a
process for how we do that. But we do
procurement on a regular basis to hire
people with uh expertise in different
areas. And so I imagine we'd issue a
request for proposals uh and vet
candidates the same way we do when we
hire consultants to provide engineering
or financial support. what whatever we
do. Yeah, I think that was one of my
questions is would this be a cityapp
appointed real estate firm that this
does all of the uh real estate sales or
would it just be every single time we
want to sell a property it's just open
to all realators? I I think that for the
the sake of efficiency, we'd probably
hire someone for a period of time, but
also the city doesn't have a lot of real
estate that it's trying to sell on a
regular basis. Um, and I I don't think
that uh that that would be um a thing
ongoing. I I'll say that for for this uh
this is really born out of the lack of
uh interest in station 6 property. Um
that property received one sealed bid
response and I did not feel that that
was sign sufficient
um to only have one response. And so
this is a way to get more responses.
Yeah. I I just I I guess I would just
hope that we would still have the
ability of the intention of what that
property becomes. That's also through a
whole zoning process. Uh and so um and
that information that we've collected
related to zoning uh for that particular
parcel would be part of the sale. And
typically sales of pro properties in the
city of Langu Lancaster are contingent
have contingencies related to them
getting zoning approval for anything
that they would use. The property for
which is the opportunity for the public
to weigh in if they don't like the
concept that's being there. And so we
would likely sign a sales agreement that
would be contingent upon them getting
the approvals that they need. And if
they don't get them, then the property
wouldn't be sold. That is a very
standard practice. Uh, thank you. And
that answers some of my questions, but
I'll look forward to discussing this in
more. Yeah. If you want to send a
followup um, councelor Amed of other
questions that you have, I'll make sure
to get that out to council before our
next meeting so you have that
information. Okay.
My questions. Thank you. Are there any
further questions from council as a
whole?
Questions from the public?
First.
Yes. Thing bird. Um, I think council
needs to be very cautious in what
they're doing. I think this goes under
the administration code. I think uh to
once you put that in place as one of the
things you would be deciding is who has
the authority to make those decisions.
So if it becomes the administration then
council it's not in your hand. I think
that number one we would need to look at
a list of properties that the city has.
Number two we have a record of changing
things for one thing. I understand it's
station six that we are, you know, um,
trying to get rid of and we in the city
have a very good habit of changing how
we do business for one thing and it
doesn't work out always. Uh, for
instance, the zoning, especially when we
came to the um Airbnb or you know,
shorting houses changed in one meeting
and we changed it again because it
didn't work. I think caution council
needs to be very cautious. I do
understand about the station six. I
think there still are other means out
there. I do think that we all know that
once the city would sell a property and
it goes before zoning, the zoning is
picked by council and the mayor. So why
wouldn't you, you know, they always have
that option of appealing or seeking a
variance to have it change to do what
they want. I mean, if we're not putting
stipulations in the deed on what that
property can
become, I think we do lose what you were
asking about, Councilman Hamemed. I
would also like to see a list of
properties that the city owns and maybe
any that they are considering selling. I
mean, maybe at this time it's only that
one, but we all know once we give up
that power from council to the
administration, you don't come back to
it. And I think this was set aside in
the home rule under the administration
code that you can put that um I don't
think it was set from home rule to say
this is something that we want. I think
one of the things that you need to
understand about home rule is that the
administration has to come up with
administration code on how we function
and a lot of things that we asked about
in the home rule was going to be
addressed through the administration
code which council has to adopt. I don't
think we got there yet. So to put stuff
in now when that has not been adopted is
jumping the gun. I mean slow down, take
some time. It's not something that needs
to happen now at this moment. Thank you.
I'll just add um it's a fair point that
this is part of administrative code
moving forward and it is true that I'm I
am presenting this and I asked our
solicitor to present this because this
is uh real property that council has
already approved the sale of that we
have not been successful selling. Uh
there is no authority related to the
sale of property that the administration
gets without council approval. Uh, and
so I want to just make that clear. Um,
and the the other piece is that um, uh,
all of the council, all of the city
properties, Miss Burke, you can find
them on, uh, by doing a query on
building blocks, and you can see all of
the properties that are owned by the
city parks, all of the buildings, etc.
There is no plan at this time to sell
any additional property. We just want to
sell this one that council approved last
year that we still have not sold. And
just and just um in reference even when
we talked about the redevelopment
authority when we're um they're taking
people's homes, they don't just give it
to the they have a realer that comes out
to sell it and different people get to
bid on it. So keep that in mind. So this
is city property that we own. So I would
keep that in mind.
really fast.
Yes. And and it is a competitive market.
Um and there are a lot of um programs
not being used for firsttime home buyers
and there are a lot of families that
could use properties across the city
that is being taken by biders. Um
there's a reason why the city
precluded this uh from or or from using
real estate agents. there there is a
reason why. So I I want you to really
really look at what we're saying because
it's very very important. Decisions
cannot be reversed and a lot of citizens
residents in Lancaster are very much
affected by this administration because
of
changes. So, I want you to think about
that really good, especially our
children and grandb
babies. Tony Dash, 700 block on New
Holland Avenue. Um,
[Music]
so this is concerning to me because the
way I see this is as creating a method
of private sale for public goods.
Um there is a reason I think the bidding
process is in place and there as far as
I understand there's nothing prohibiting
us from being more open about our
advertising. We're just required to
advertise in a newspaper or general
circulation. This should not be the way
we handle this because when you use a
realer I mean I recognize the argument
like it's valid. you do open up the
potential for a transaction to occur,
but you also channelize those
communications. You don't ensure that
this is an open, transparent public or
process for the whole public. And I
understand that it is arduous to try and
sell a property. I frankly do not think
we should sell station 6. I think there
are other solutions to do with station
6. Um, but I'm generally frustrated in
right now us putting forward amendments
like this or I know this as an
administration bill, but this or a
recent zoning amendment that was not
presented at the last meeting because
there's some pause elsewhere, but just
expressing a frustration I have when we
we the city planning commission were
made aware of the disapproval or at
least I wasn't. I I I've listened to the
meeting twice and it wasn't discussed
that the that zoning amendment had been
disapproved and I feel like what we're
working through right now is a bunch of
ad hoc things and we need to focus on
these bulk products like the entire
zoning code and the entire
administration code. Um I think we're
moving too fast. I think that there are
valid questions to be had about this
process because it could be exclusionary
to the public and create solutions that
the whole public does not feel
confidence in because a realer could
reach out to somebody and sell somebody
on a dream that the public doesn't want.
Doesn't the use might be allowed but it
doesn't mean that it's something that
the public's looking forward to. So I do
think the bidding process is the one we
should stick with at this current moment
in time. I as a resident am open to hear
hearing about other alternatives
potentially like this in the future. But
I think this this is a this is a big
shift from the way government's supposed
to operate. This is this is trying to
operate government like a business and
government should operate like a
government.
Mr. Dastra, just to clarify a point, um
the rent commission uh zoning was not
disapproved. It was disapproved by the
county planning commission. Oh, I Okay,
you didn't specify that. I just My
apologies. This body this body did not
no they they approved planning
commission approved I'm just expressing
the frustration we weren't made aware of
that at planning commission understood
okay uh I will just say that you know we
are planning to planning to bring the
first trunch and I think councelor
reported on this as part of his
transition committee report that we're
going to plan to bring the first trunch
of an admin code changes to council um
in June June um followed successfully an
August September time frame with a
second trunch. Um this can wait until
then. I am really just trying to fulfill
the wishes of this body that you wanted
to sell. We collectively decided that
that was what the need was. So it's
fine. Post another public bid. Then we
shouldn't change the process just yet.
and pausing this 3
months. We we need to have bigger
communic community to conversation about
the idea of changing these public
processes. Thank you. That's what we're
here for. Thank you.
I just want to add I just want to add
real quickly. Um there are nonprofit
organizations such as
churches, multiple a substantial amount
of churches throughout the city of
Lancaster that could use that. That is
true. and we could and and they're
they're not being I I work with multiple
churches. We could decide you're not
reaching out to them. We could give it
away. Uh and at the same time, I would
say that we're also trying to pay for a
lot of things. This is a conversation
about the future use of this parcel.
There there was no we sent it out to
every housing organization in the city
uh that had been doing work. There were
no proposals that came from any housing
organ nonprofit housing
organiz because they have a lot of
projects that they're currently working
on. And so there wasn't there wasn't any
interest. Uh there was a commercial use
that was proposed that was not a public
use. Uh and it was one bid. And so just
to say there was a lot of effort that
was put into getting this out to our
nonprofit partners. Um there was
conversation about um uh sale prices. I
mean all of that could be negotiated uh
in terms of a use that was in um that
the neighborhood would be excited about
that council would be excited about that
the administration would be excited
about that would go through zoning. Um
and that just didn't come to bear. And I
don't think it's because of lack of
interest. I think it's because of lack
of resources at this particular moment.
A lot of the organizations have really
big projects that they're already
working on with ARPA funds that they
need to complete and some of those
projects haven't even started yet and
the city is in desperate need of
lowincome subsidized housing and I don't
think that HUD or the housing authority
would be uh more than happy to grab this
to put some housing for the people in
the city of Lancaster. They are
desperate. There's more and more
homeless people out there. So, I don't
think you're uh drawing the right
audience. So, take that into
consideration. Thank you, Mr. Gomez.
Thank good evening. Good evening. Um me
again. I live off 30. Um Diane Desmond.
Your name? Yes, Diane Desmond. Hi.
Um, so I just wanted to further urge
council to consider um when you're
looking at this proposal to consider a
checks and balances system to ensure
that current residents are prioritized
over profit. I know that it looks like a
very lucrative opportunity, but there
could be some very real consequences for
the current residents of the city. Um,
and I also would urge you to consider
how this could potentially exclude
voices of the public in this process of
what happens in their own city. Thank
you. Thank you. Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Um, so,
so since this is a
bill, I believe that
I'll make a motion to move it to full
counsel for
consideration for the 8th.
Second. All those in favor? I I Thank
you, Council President. Um that is all
community planning has this evening.
Thank you very much, Councelor Craig. Uh
the last committee this evening is the
committee of the whole. We have three
items on our agenda this evening. uh
counselors. The first is resolution
number
2425. This is author raising a flag
raising to mark Puerto Rican Heritage
Month. Um an application has been made
in a timely manner uh for a flag
raising. Um and this is I had it in
front of me and I accidentally closed it
during the course of our meeting and I
apologize.
Um an application was put
in. I'm totally missing who submitted
the application.
Goodness
[Music]
gracious. It doesn't say it, which is
why I missed it. I apologize. But a
request was put in to uh fly the Puerto
Rican flag or do the I'm sorry, the late
hour is getting to me. To raise the
Puerto Rican flag in honor of uh part
of Yeah. Nope. Uh on I'm sorry. November
18th, 2025 with a rain date of November
19th, 2025. Thank you very much. Uh, and
this was actually uh requested by
councelor Jamie Roy. Thank you.
Okay. Thank
you. I'm
sorry. I'm a little It's been a very
long day and I appreciate that. So
anyway, this to raise the Puerto Rican
flag on the date of November 18th uh in
front of city hall. Councilors, any
comments on the resolution?
Thank you. Comments from the public on
the resolution.
Just one quick,
just one quick question. Um, November
18th through the 19th, is that like a a
mark date representing anything in the
history of Puerto Rico that we can raise
it on that date or can you accept a more
um historical
date? Council Roy, this state was chosen
for a particular reason. Yep. Uh
typically that week is the is considered
National Puerto Rican week. Okay, that's
what I wanted to know. Thank you. You
Yep. And so the date of the flag flag
raising would be the 18th and we're
reserving the 19th for a rain date.
Okay. Any additional comments from the
public? Hearing none, I will make a
motion to move resolution number 24 to
our next council meeting on the 8th.
Second. A motion and a second. All those
in favor? I. Any opposed? Okay. Thank
you. Um, next item on our agenda for
committee of the whole is council
resolution number 23, 2025
um recognizing uh April um a sexual
assault awareness month in the city of
Lancaster. This is an annual resolution
of recognition um that uh I am
presenting. Um we typically uh invite um
folks from our YW.CA
um sexual assault prevention center to
come to council to address and talk
about any uh current events they have
going on for the month. Um statistics
and information that's pertinent to city
residents. Um and it's important that we
uh note this every year. Any council
comments on this
resolution from the public?
hearing. None. I'll make a motion that
we move council resolution 23 2025 to
our next meeting on the 8th. Second. A
motion and a second. All in favor? I.
Any opposed?
And lastly, we have resolution number 32
2025 recognizing Lafayette and Lancaster
bysentennial. Um, this is an interesting
historical uh resolution. Uh this is a
um a resolution designating July 27th
through the 29th as Lafayette days in
the city of Lancaster in recogn
recognition of the bicesentennial of
Lafayette's visit to Lancaster on his
farewell tour uh 50 years after the
American Revolution. Um there are um
many events happening um around the city
um and also at Rockford for this event
and this would uh make this an official
designation in the city of Lancaster for
this historic event. Any additional
council comments on the
resolution from the quickly dwindling
public hearing none. I'll make a motion
to move this to council on our April
22nd meeting. Second. Second. All those
in favor? Um, thank you very much. Um,
that is the end of our committee agenda.
Mr. Harris, you've submitted your
clerk's report in writing. Is that
correct? I have, Madam President. Thank
you. That's available to all members of
council. Uh, having concluded our
business, I'll hear a motion to adjurnn.
Motion to adjurnn. I heard a motion. I'm
sorry. I heard a second in there. Thank
you very much. All those in favor? Hi.
Thank you. We're
[Music]
happy birthday team.
One of the many
[Music]
Okay.
Not at